<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A modest plea for the Lords Day or rather the summe of the plea made by divines for the Lords Day as the Christian Sabbath, against those who contend for the old Sabbath of the seventh day, in order from the creation / by J.C., D.D.</title>
            <author>Collinges, John, 1623-1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33970</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5327</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43109</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">26823052</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 26823052</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109812</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33970)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109812)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1714:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A modest plea for the Lords Day or rather the summe of the plea made by divines for the Lords Day as the Christian Sabbath, against those who contend for the old Sabbath of the seventh day, in order from the creation / by J.C., D.D.</title>
                  <author>Collinges, John, 1623-1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 132 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained and tightly bound, with print show-through and loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sunday --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sabbath --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Rest --  Religious aspects --  Christianity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109812:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A MODEST PLEA FOR THE LORDS DAY: OR RATHER The <hi>Summe of the</hi> PLEA made by <hi>Divines</hi> for the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> as the <hi>Chriſtian Sabbath:</hi> AGAINST Thoſe who contend for the <hi>Old Sabbath</hi> of the <hi>Seventh Day,</hi> in other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the <hi>Creation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>J. C.</hi> D. D.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mar. 2.28.</hi>
               </bibl> The Son of Man is Lord alſo of the Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>th.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Acts 6.14.</hi>
               </bibl> We have heard him ſay, That this Jeſus of Nazareth ſhall deſtroy this place, and ſhall change the Cuſtoms which <hi>Moſes</hi> delivered us.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. 4 10.</hi>
               </bibl> You obſerve <hi>DAYES,</hi> and Moneths, and Times, and Years.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 11.</hi>
               </bibl> I am afraid of you, leſt I have beſtowed labour in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1669.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:109812:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109812:2"/>
            <head>To thoſe <hi>Chriſtians</hi> (eſpecially my Neighbours) in the County of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> who are zealous for the Obſervation of the <hi>Seventh Day Sabbath.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y heart's deſire, and prayer to God for you all, is that you might be ſaved:</hi> For, <hi>I bear you record, that you have a zeal of God;</hi> only if I make a doubt <hi>whether it be according to knowledge</hi> or no: yea, if I tell you, I verily believe it is <hi>not according to knowledge,</hi> I am ſure (your inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unity is ſuch) that you will pardon it to me, conſidering that my own <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> is differing from you, and <hi>Charity</hi> (which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb facs="tcp:109812:3"/> begins at home) will not allow me to judge my ſelf to practiſe upon <hi>ignorance;</hi> though I am alſo one o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them who but <hi>know in part,</hi> yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hope I deſire to practiſe according to my knowledge: Which if you will b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo charitable as to ſuppoſe, I muſt judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your zeal not to be according to <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge.</hi> And let me tell you, as there is no more ſacred <hi>fire</hi> than that of <hi>zea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> when it hath its <hi>due fuel,</hi> and is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in a <hi>juſt and good cauſe;</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there is no more dangerous fire when i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hath a <hi>miſtaken object.</hi> The zealou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſoul <hi>runneth,</hi> and as the man who run<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth, if he be in a right way come quicker than another to his journey end; but if he be out of his way, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is ſooner than another at a further di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtance from home: So it is with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>zealous ſpirit.</hi> I muſt profeſs, let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> perſon be of what perſwaſion he will I muſt have a reverence for him, if perceive that he differeth from me ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Conſcience, becauſe he <hi>dareth not t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:109812:3"/> ſin againſt God.</hi> It is a noble temper to be afraid of ſin. If a perſon pretends <hi>conſcience for a particular opinion and practice,</hi> and in the mean time be a common <hi>drunkard, ſwearer, liar, blaſphemer, unclean perſon, one that lives as it were without God in the World, making no conſcience of reading the Scripture, praying, bringing up and governing his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily in the nurture and fear of the Lord,</hi> only pretends <hi>conſcience</hi> as to <hi>baptizing of Children,</hi> keeping the <hi>Seventh day Sabbath;</hi> this man is an hypocrite, and diſſembles with God and men for there is an <hi>uniformity in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> and it would certainly oblige him to avoid known and confeſsed ſins, as much as what he doth fancy is a ſin, and as much oblige him to all, as to any known duty. But where I ſee a Chriſtian <hi>walking cloſe with God</hi> in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of his converſation, and differing from me in this or that point, becauſe he thinks he cannot without ſin believe
<pb facs="tcp:109812:4"/> and practiſe what I do; I cannot but love and honour him, and be very far from their Religion who think it the beſt and moſt Goſpel way to cudgel him into my Perſwaſion: A <hi>Gaol,</hi> or a <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Faggots</hi> never yet cured an erring Conſcience. Such Brethren though <hi>overtaken with a fault</hi> are certainly (according to the Apoſtles counſell) to <hi>be reſtored in the ſpirit of meekneſs,</hi> and to be dealt with, (like rational Creatures) <hi>argued,</hi> and <hi>treated,</hi> and <hi>perſwaded</hi> out of their miſtakes, not cudgelled out of them. This (Brethren) hath cauſed me to ſend this little Book amongſt you; ſo penned, as I think you will not judge it to have any thing of bitterneſs in it, and in ſo ſmall a volume, as I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deſpair but that you will beſtow the reading of it, nor will it ask you long time: You will find in it, the moſt of what hath been ſaid by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines in this caſe: I have contracted their larger Diſcourſes that I might
<pb facs="tcp:109812:4"/> not tire your patience, and made what they have ſaid (in <hi>Latine</hi> or in more Scholaſtick terms) plain to you by a free and familiar ſtyle. The ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of your diſſent doth certainly call to you for the uſe of all poſsible means to finde out what indeed is the Truth of God in this point; and there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a greater witneſs againſt you, of your want of ſincerity, than an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſs to read or hear what hath been, or is or ſhall be ſaid againſt you. For though indeed there be ſome Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Faith, ſome Principles of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, about which it is a Chriſtians <hi>wiſdom</hi> not to admit diſputes, yet this is <hi>not</hi> ſuch; 'tis no Fundamental in Religion <hi>that the ſeventh Day from the Creation is the Sabbath:</hi> It is none of thoſe points in which you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not erre without breaking your <hi>union</hi> with the Head Chriſt, yet is it no light point, for it breaks communion with <hi>all</hi> Churches, and that is no light mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: And the Scripture ſayes <hi>we are
<pb facs="tcp:109812:5"/> members of Chriſt, and members one of another.</hi> Although an erring Conſcience obligeth him that is troubled with it, to do nothing againſt it, yet certainly he that hath it, or hath rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon but to ſuſpect he hath it, ſtands highly obliged to uſe all means to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it; and although the differing complexion of a Chriſtians Conſcience may oblige him for a time, to walk divided from his Brethren, yet he ought not to do it without many <hi>thoughts of heart,</hi> becauſe of his <hi>diviſion;</hi> and while he <hi>walks alone</hi> in obedience to his Conſcience, he ought alſo to <hi>ſit alone,</hi> and to <hi>keep ſilence.</hi> To ſit alone pondering with himſelf, what is ſaid on both ſides, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice, weighing arguments in the ballance of the Sanctuary, <hi>compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſpiritual things with ſpiritual.</hi> And to <hi>keep ſilence,</hi> both as to the <hi>publiſhing</hi> his <hi>ſingular</hi> and <hi>novel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>ns,</hi> (keeping to that excellent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom. 14.22.
<pb facs="tcp:109812:5"/> Haſt thou faith? have it to thy ſelf, before God.)</hi> (It is a mad fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of ſome, who think that every opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in Religion is worth breaking the Churches peace for) and alſo <hi>keeping ſilence</hi> as to <hi>inveighing againſt and reviling others,</hi> otherwiſe perſwaded and practiſing: For, <hi>which way went the Spirit of God from the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of their Brethren unto them?</hi> And beſides, who knowes not that <hi>there is the ſame diſtance</hi> betwixt <hi>their brethren and them?</hi> and none can uſurp ſuch authority, but thoſe who will arrogate to themſelves <hi>infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> and take away the <hi>judgement</hi> of <hi>diſcerning,</hi> which is the very <hi>root</hi> and <hi>baſis</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi> You know <hi>Brethren,</hi> what Fetters I have upon me as to my <hi>publick Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry.</hi> If I were free, I queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I by it ſhould have any capacity to ſerve your ſouls, while you are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this miſtake: If I may do it with theſe Printed Papers, it will be no
<pb facs="tcp:109812:6"/> ſmall ſatisfaction to me; if not, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>my work is with the Lord, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my judgement is with my God</hi> I think ſcarce any of you think I have any prejudice againſt you, many of you may believe, I have a great kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for you. The good Lord bring us all in this point, to <hi>think</hi> and <hi>ſpeak</hi> the <hi>ſame thing,</hi> and to walk in the ſame Way.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Friend and Servant in the Goſpel of our Lord Ieſus,</hi> John Collenges.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109812:6"/>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The occaſion of the Diſcourſe, and what moved the Author to it.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F in the following Diſcourſe I had deſigned to have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantaged my Name in a printed Book, I had cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly made choice of <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Subject,</hi> or handled this <hi>in another manner</hi> than I have. I know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing left for an Author on this ſubject, it hath been ſo variouſly and learnedly handled by eminent Authors: Nothing is to be add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to what Mr. <hi>Ley</hi> hath ſaid to juſtifie the application of the Name <hi>Sabbath</hi> to the <hi>Lords day.</hi> Nor to what Dr. <hi>Twiſs,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sheppard,</hi> Mr. <hi>Caudry,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Warren,</hi> have ſaid for the <hi>Morality of it,</hi> for the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal</hi> or <hi>expiration</hi> of the <hi>Jewiſh Sabbath,</hi> for the <hi>change of it</hi> to the <hi>firſt day of the Week.</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:109812:7"/> Mr. <hi>Sheppard</hi> and Mr. <hi>Caudry</hi> have not lef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Oc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d</hi> or <hi>Brabourn</hi> nor Mr. <hi>Warren</hi> left Mr. <hi>Tilham</hi> a rag to cover the nakedneſs of their faireyes; nor is ought to be added to wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Dr. <hi>Young</hi> hath ſaid to the <hi>primitive obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> of it. For the practical ſanctification of it, all the Authors aforeſaid have ſpoke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fully, to which may be added Dr. <hi>Bound,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bernard,</hi> and lately Mr. <hi>Wells:</hi> To ſay nothing of the controverſial part handled by the aforeſaid Authors, againſt <hi>Heylin, Primroſe, Ironſide,</hi> and all of that party who would make our <hi>Sabbath</hi> but an ordinary <hi>Church-holiday:</hi> ſo that indeed there is not room left for a new <hi>Author</hi> to croud in, bringing any thing new in this caſe.</p>
               <p>Nor ſhall this diſcourſe pretend to any thing of that nature. I look upon it as our great diſadvantage in reference to moſt of our brethren, who contend for the <hi>Jewiſh Sabbath</hi> to be ſtill in force, that what is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſaid in the caſe (which is abundantl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> enough) is either ſpoken ſo <hi>learnedly</hi> as they cannot underſtand it: or elſe <hi>hidden in large volumes</hi> of conſiderable price, which either ordinary people want money to buy, or <hi>time</hi> to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ad, or <hi>judgement</hi> to finde out. All there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall pretend to, is in a plain familiar
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109812:7"/> Diſcourſe to preſent our brethren with the ſumme of what hath been far more fully and learnedly diſcourſed by others. To which, that which hath been the next oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion is my preſent leiſure, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God caſting me in a place, where I obſerve very many, and thoſe whoſe hearts I would charitably think God had touched with a ſenſe of Religion, and who I truſt truely fear God, and love the Lord Jeſus, have received impreſſions, leading them to a great zeal for the old Sabbath. The conſequents of which opinion, I look upon as very ſad, theſe Chriſtians <hi>breaking communion</hi> with all Chriſtian Churches in the World: and depriving themſelves of the advantage they might have from commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with us on the Lords day. For though I have known ſome of that opinion, who yet on the Lords day would come to hear the <hi>Word preached</hi> and <hi>joyn in Prayer</hi> with other Congregations, yet I perceive another ſpirit in many of my preſent Neighbours. And beſides if (being poſſeſſed of that opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) they did come, it would not be with ſuch preparation, nor in ſuch a Conſcience of what they did as were requiſite for ſuch as expect a bleſſing from or in ſuch dutyes.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109812:8"/> God hath pleaſed at preſent to call me to ſit down in ſilence as to my publick Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, that I might in ſomething ſerve my generation, and be uſefull to the Souls of others, I have put my pen to Paper in this cauſe; nor have I had any other motive whatſoever: but if it might be to do good to ſome Soul or other; or if I cannot cure, yet at leaſt (through the ſtrength of God), to ſtop the ſpreading of this diſeaſe, amongſt Chriſtians.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The firſt Conſideration. That God hath no more glory, nor the Souls of Chriſtians any more reall advantage, from the obſervation of the Seventh day from the Creation, than from the obſervation of the Lords Day as the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Sabbath; nor can be any pretence of this nature but that of ſtricter Obedience to the Commandment.</head>
               <p>I Take it to be an excellent notion of that holy and eminent Servant of God, Mr. <hi>Thomas Sheppard,</hi> that the thing which makes a Law morall, <hi>is a goodneſs in the thing, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109812:8"/> precedent to the command, yet cauſed by the eternal will of God.</hi> Ceremonial Laws were therefore good becauſe commanded, but the matter of every Moral Law muſt have ſome goodneſs, that is ſome equity, ſome ſuitableneſs in it to the nature, and to the Concernment of men and women, preceding the command, eſpecially if we rightly conſider man as he ſtands related to God, and to his Neighbour, as he is made up of Body and Soul, both ordained to an eternal exiſtence. The light of nature ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us, that there is a God, and but one God, he, our Creator, Preſerver, Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, an Eſſence of glorious Majeſty, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and holineſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If we had never heard of the firſt, ſecond, or third Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Nature would have told us, it was fit we ſhould give the higheſt homage of our Souls to him alone, worſhip him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will, not blaſpheme his Name, nor uſe any thing related to him irreverently, which is the ſubſtance of the three firſt Commandments. The ſame will be yielded as to the 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, and 10. The very light of Nature, would have ſhewed us a fitneſs, and ſutableneſs in the things there commanded, to humane So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109812:9"/> if we never had heard of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment. The ſame light of Nature alſo would have ſhewn us, that ſome time muſt be ſpent in the ſervice of God. That it was reaſonable ſome due proportion of time ſhould be ſo ſanctified. Indeed that this ſhould be a ſeventh part rather than a ſixth, Nature would not have ſhewn us, that is, morall, poſitive, but being directed, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will preſently allow it <hi>equal, holy, juſt</hi> and <hi>good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Original goodneſs in the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a ſeventh part of our time as holy to the Lord muſt lye either in this,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That from ſuch a Religious Obſervation our Creator will reap ſome glory.</hi>— Or this,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That from it, Man, as to Soul or Body will reap ſome conſiderable advantage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Both which are moſt undoubtedly true, both as to ſome proportion of time, and as to a <hi>ſeventh</hi> rather than a <hi>leſſer part</hi> of our time. The honour we bring to God by <hi>Acts of Worſhip,</hi> being only in the publiſhing of his Name, and Works. The more frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we do exalt his Name, and publiſh his Works, the more Glory we bring him.</p>
               <p>Again, Ordinances being the way through which our Lord Jeſus uſeth to paſs, the more
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109812:9"/> we have of Religious Duties and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the more advantage ariſeth to our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Souls, if we be not wanting to our ſelves. But now what reall advantage any ſoul can have from the ſanctification of the laſt more than of the firſt day of the week, will poſe the moſt ſerious Chriſtian to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine: Is his Soul to be advantaged by Praying, Hearing, Singing, breaking Bread? All theſe certainly are done on the Lords day, and with this advantage in a far fuller communion of Chriſtians, than thoſe have who keep the ſixth day, as to which the far larger part of Chriſtians, and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, yea and the ſevereſt livers of them, are not ſatisfied. The only thing which I can think of, as ſeeming in the leaſt to abate the edge of this conſideration, is, <hi>That God is more glorified, becauſe a ſtricter Obedience is given to his revealed Will.</hi> And indeed <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> hath taught us, <hi>That the Lord hath not ſo great delight in Burnt-Offerings and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices as he hath in our obeying his voyce; that to Obey is better than Sacrifice, and to hearken than the fat of Rams.</hi> Now our Brethren pretend a more ſtrict obedience to the will of God, in the ſanctification of the <hi>ſeventh</hi> than in the ſanctification of the <hi>firſt day:</hi> I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109812:10"/> ſhall therefore in the next Chapter argu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that caſe with them. In the mean time, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is worthy of our Brethrens ſecond thought<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whether under the Goſpel it be uſual with God to enjoyn his People Precepts of <hi>mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Obedience,</hi> I mean ſuch from whence their Souls ſhall reap no advantage, nor he any glory, only in this as we ſhew our <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the will of God.</hi> Our gracious God hath made his yoke eaſie by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding us nothing but ſuch, by perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which, we further glorifie him, than by a meer Obedience, and from which alſo we reap ſome reall advantage to our Bodies or Souls. Such I am ſure are all the other moral Precepts, by a performance of them, we really (beſides obedience to the will of God) do our ſelves or others ſome good, and bring God ſome reall glory fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than by the acknowledging of him our Soveraign, and yielding him a ſuitable ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. But as to this, there can be no ſuch pretence, neither Souls nor Bodies of our ſelves or others are more advantaged, nor God more honoured by our obſervation of the ſeventh, than of the firſt day, nor is God more honoured, if it doth not appear he is more obeyed. It is agreed on both hands,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109812:10"/> that one intire day ought to be ſanctified, by the ſolemn performance of all duties of inſtituted Worſhip, both publickly and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately, Reading the Word, praying, preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, hearing, adminiſtring and receiving the holy Sacraments, ſinging of Pſalms, viſiting, and adminiſtring to the neceſſities of the ſick, and of the poor. Now I ſay it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be imagined what good our ſelves, or others ſhall reap more by the performance of theſe duties on the ſeventh than on the firſt day: Nor what honour God ſhall have if it doth not appear, that a ſtricter obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is yielded to the command of God by the ſanctification of the ſeventh, than by the ſanctification of the firſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> That God hath no where required of Chriſtians, the obſervation of the Seventh day. The fourth Commandment, though it requires a Seventh day, and ſuch ſeventh day as is of Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, yet it doth no more require the Seventh, than the firſt day of the Week.</head>
               <p>THere can be no pretence for a further Obedience to the command of God in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109812:11"/> the obſervation of the ſeventh day in orde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from the Creation, than in the obſervatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the firſt, but from the letter of the fourth Commandment, as to which it is thus far agreed betwixt us and our Brethren.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That it is in the power of God only to make a day holy.</hi> No man can lay mens Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences under an obligation, that it ſhall be ſin for them not to labour on this or that day, or not to ſpend ſuch a day in publick and private dutyes of Divine Worſhip, but by Authority from God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That the fourth Commandment is morall and perpetuall,</hi> not <hi>ceremonial and temporary</hi> either in <hi>whole,</hi> or in <hi>part.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. That the ſence of it is <hi>plain,</hi> and <hi>lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> not <hi>myſtical</hi> only.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That as it requireth ſome <hi>ſolemn time</hi> to be ſet apart for the Worſhip of God, ſo expreſſely,
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>A whole Day.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>One whole Day of Seven.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Such a Day as God hath inſtituted.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>So that we are far nearer agreement with our Brethren of this perſwaſion, than with <hi>Heylin, Primroſe,</hi> &amp;c. and the reſt of that party, who will have the Commandment <hi>ceremonial</hi> either in <hi>whole</hi> or in <hi>part</hi> (and ſo
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:109812:11"/> loſe us one of the ten Commandments) or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hoſe who overſtraining two or three <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorical expreſſions</hi> in <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> would make the ſenſe myſticall, Chriſt to be the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and the Precept only to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the <hi>Sanctification of the Name of Chriſt,</hi> (a modern dream juſtifiable by no Reaſon, Scripture, nor Authority.) We are agreed with our Brethren, That the fourth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment <hi>is a Precept requiring the ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of a ſeventh part of our time unto the Lord for ever, and ſuch a ſeventh part as we ſhall find his direction for.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that the <hi>fourth commandement</hi> doth primarily require the <hi>ſanctification</hi> of the <hi>ſeventh day</hi> in order from the Creation, is that in which alone we differ from our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. Let us therefore without paſſion, candidly conſult the Precept, and ſee what there is in it, which can juſtifie our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns zeal in this caſe. The Precept runs thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Remember the Sabbath day, to keep it holy, ſix dayes thou ſhalt labour, and do all thy work, but the Seventh day is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God, in it thou ſhalt not do any work, thou, nor thy ſon, nor thy daughter, nor thy man-ſervant, nor thy maid-ſervant, nor thy Cattel,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109812:12"/> nor thy ſtranger, that is within thy gate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> For in ſix dayes the Lord made Heaven <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Earth, the Sea, and all that in them is, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſted the ſeventh day. Wherefore the Lord bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed the Sabbath day, and hallowed it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It (poſſibly) is ſome diſadvantage in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> controverſie, that moſt of our Brethren a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not skilled in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> language, in whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this Precept was Originally wrote. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lay much ſtreſs upon the word <hi>Sabbat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and the particle <hi>the,</hi> beyond what indee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the letter of the Precept will bear: It ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not therefore be amiſs to let our Brethre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> know theſe two things by way of pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſe,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the term <hi>Sabbath</hi> in the <hi>Hebre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſignifieth no more than <hi>Reſt,</hi> and a day o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſabbath</hi> is no more than a <hi>day of reſt.</hi> Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the term Sabbath ſignifies no more than <hi>reſt</hi> is evident to him that either attends the derivation of the word, or the uſage of the ſame word in many Scriptures. <hi>Lev.</hi> 25.6. where it is applyed to the years of <hi>Jubilee, Lev.</hi> 26.43. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.21. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.7. It is uſed to ſignifie <hi>a reſt from ſtrife, Prov.</hi> 20.3. and that <hi>reſt from labour</hi> which a wounded man hath, <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.19. it is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109812:12"/> uſed to expreſs the <hi>reſting place of Thorns</hi> laid up to be burned, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.7. Now becauſe thoſe dayes, which it pleaſed God to ſet apart for himſelf, were dayes in which he did require a ceſſation from labour to that end, that they might better attend Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious dutyes, theſe dayes were called <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths,</hi> and that as well before the giving of the Law upon <hi>Sinai, Exod.</hi> 16.25, 26, 29. as after in innumerable Texts. So as the word is indifferently uſed, to ſignifie the <hi>weekly Sabbath</hi> as thoſe other <hi>holy dayes</hi> which God appointed the <hi>Jews</hi> twice in Holy Writt, we find the word (with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle alteration) doubled, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.23.35.2. we tranſlate it <hi>a Sabbath of Reſt.</hi> In the Hebrew it is but the doubling of the ſame word or words, or of a word from the ſame root, and of the ſame ſignificancy, <hi>A reſt of reſt,</hi> ſignifying it was not to be a <hi>bare ceſſation from labour,</hi> but an <hi>holy, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious</hi> reſt. So as the fourth Commandement is no more than <hi>Keep holy a day of Reſt.</hi> And becauſe God had inſtituted but one ſuch day in the revolution of a Week, therefore by an uſual figure the word doth ſometimes ſignifie <hi>a week,</hi> as <hi>Lev.</hi> 23.15.25.8. and ſo in the New Teſtament. But
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109812:13"/> that uſage of the word in this caſe w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have nothing as yet to do with.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A ſecond thing which our Brethre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould know, and obſerve, is, That thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> little particles <hi>a</hi> and <hi>the</hi> are Engliſh par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, not found in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> but put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by tranſlation, to make up the ſenſe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our way of ſpeaking, the <hi>Hebre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> hath no more than <hi>Remember to keep holy d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Reſt,</hi> or <hi>day of Sabbath;</hi> and it is indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent whether (according to our Engliſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> way of ſpeaking) we put in <hi>a</hi> or <hi>the;</hi> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> can any argument on either ſide be fetche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from thoſe ſupplyes to the Text.</p>
               <p>Theſe things being premiſed, we ſay That there are three things or four whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Fourth Commandement requireth o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> us.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That we ſhould keep ſome ſolemn time, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> a time of holy Reſt unto the Lord.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>That it ſhould be one day of ſeven, a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth part of our time.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>That it ſhould be an intire day.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>That it ſhould be ſuch an intire day of ſeven as God hath appointed.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>But that this day ſhould be the ſevent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> day in order from the Creation, we ſay falleth not (at leaſt primarily under the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109812:13"/> Fourth Commandment) I ſay <hi>primarily</hi> not, <hi>ſecondarily</hi> it doth, as that was the day which God had appointed to the <hi>Jews:</hi> Now we ſay,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That this <hi>is not a ſingularity,</hi> but divers divine Precepts, both of thoſe which were temporary to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and of thoſe which are of perpetual concernment, have juſt ſuch an interpretation allowed even by our Brethren, and by all judicious Chriſtians. God commanded, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.5.11. <hi>You ſhall offer all your ſacrifices; only in the place which the Lord your God ſhall chooſe.</hi> I would ask our brethren whether this Precept did not oblige them; to offer their Sacrifices in the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> while that laſted, and in <hi>the Temple</hi> afterwards when God had choſen that, and in <hi>Ezra's</hi> Temple when that was builded. You ſhall remember ſaith God to keep holy a <hi>Sabbath day,</hi> one day <hi>in ſeven</hi> for an <hi>holy reſt,</hi> ſuch a one, as God ſhall chooſe for <hi>a Sabbath,</hi> why muſt this be the <hi>ſeventh</hi> from the <hi>Creation</hi> only, and not that only till God ſhould chooſe <hi>another,</hi> which done, the Commandment as much obligeth to that. We ſay in the ſecond Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment God requires of us, obſervance of the Acts of Inſtituted Worſhip, which with the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109812:14"/> 
                  <hi>Jews</hi> quite differed from ours. Yet the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mand, obliged both them to <hi>ſacrifice,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> us to <hi>preach, hear, receive the Lords Supper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> How ſo? The Commandment only require<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of us in the generall to worſhip God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will. The fifth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, requires us to <hi>Honour the King,</hi> whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it was given, the <hi>Jews</hi> were bound to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour <hi>Moſes</hi> their chief Magiſtrate at tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> time, and many years after, they were bound to honour <hi>Ahaz, Hezekiah,</hi> and all in force<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the ſame Precept. God requires by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Fourth Commandment, that his People in all Ages <hi>ſhould keep holy to him a Sabbath day.</hi> He expounds himſelf thus: One day in <hi>ſeven,</hi> in which we ſhall not labour (h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> any bodily labour,) and ſuch a day as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould appoint. You will ſay then, how did the <hi>Jews</hi> know, or how ſhall we know what to keep? We anſwer, the <hi>Jew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> knew by a Law given them of the ſame Age (with that for Sacrifices) many hundreds of years before the Law given at <hi>Sinai,</hi> and by a temporary Law often repeated, and quite of another kind from the Fourth Commandment; which day muſt hold ſtill if we can neither find it <hi>expired</hi> nor <hi>repealed</hi> nor <hi>another ſubſtituted in the room of it;</hi> bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:109812:14"/> if we can find any ſuch ſacred Record. The Fourth Commandment is not deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but eſtabliſhed. That required <hi>a Sabbath, a day, one of ſeven, ſuch day as God had,</hi> or <hi>ſhould appoint.</hi> We plead only for a new ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of the particular day to the New Earth, the New World which God made by the ſending of his Son into the world; in the mean while the Fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth neither require this, nor that day otherwiſe than as that day was at that time by another Law by God ſet apart. Let us hear what our Brethren object.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Some of them have <hi>obſerved an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatical note in the Hebrew,</hi> as much as <hi>that Sabbath.</hi> Remember to keep holy the day of <hi>that Sabbath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We yield it, that the affix Π is indeed ſometimes emphatical, but hundreds of places are to be ſhewed where it is not, ſo as no argument of force can be drawn from it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But we may grant it ſo: it is not <hi>that day,</hi> but the day of <hi>that Sabbath,</hi> if the note of Emphaſis had been to the word ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying day, it had been far more to our Brethrens purpoſe. But what is it to our Brethrens purpoſe that it is the day of <hi>that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:109812:15"/> reſt,</hi> or <hi>that Sabbath?</hi> We will grant them that it is no ordinary reſt, but a ſpecial em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatical reſt, a <hi>ſpiritual, holy, religious reſt,</hi> which God requireth; not a meer ceſſation from labour, but a <hi>reſt of reſts</hi> as God ſome<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>times calls it, an <hi>holy reſt,</hi> in which we muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not think our own thoughts.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But (ſay our Brethren) <hi>you grant th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> God requires by the Fourth Commandement <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſeventh day, how can it be a ſeventh? if it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a firſt day, can the firſt be the ſeventh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> All this runs upon the forme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> miſtake, that the fourth Commandeme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> requireth the ſeventh in order from the Creation, which we have denyed; it require no more than <hi>ſuch ſeventh Day</hi> as <hi>God ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> or ſhould appoint.</hi> Suppoſe ſeven pieces o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Silver on a Table before us, either the one or other of the outermoſt pieces may be the ſeventh accordingly as we begin to count. We muſt ſuppoſe the ſeven dayes of the Week ſo to lye before the great Lord o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our time; ſurely that is the <hi>ſeventh</hi> whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God will appoint and make ſo.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe that any one of us ſhould ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to our neighbour our crop of Corn, with a reſervation to our ſelves of a <hi>ſeventh part</hi> according to the proportion of our Acres
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109812:15"/> and we ſhould ſay to them: Remember I have reſerved the <hi>ſeventh</hi> part to my ſelf, ſix parts I have ſold you, but a ſeventh is mine, you ſhall not meddle with it. Muſt this <hi>ſeventh</hi> upon ſuch a demiſe, needs be this or that Cloſe, ſurely no; but ſuch a <hi>ſeventh,</hi> as either (according to our bargain) we ſhall <hi>chooſe,</hi> or our Farmer ſhall ſet out. This is the caſe, all our time was <hi>Gods,</hi> he hath freely given us <hi>ſix parts</hi> and reſerved a <hi>ſeventh,</hi> ſuch a <hi>ſeventh,</hi> as he ſhall appoint to himſelf. Hath not God a liberty at his pleaſure to ſet out a <hi>ſeventh</hi> to us.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>But</hi> (ſay our Brethren) <hi>it muſt needs be the ſeventh in order from the Creation, for that was the day which God reſted, which is brought in the Commandement as an argument to urge upon us the ſanctification of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. That our great Creators reſting from his work of creation, is brought as an argument to induce us to the obſervation of the Sabbath we freely grant, but we ſay not as an argument for the <hi>particular day,</hi> but for the ſame <hi>proportion of time.</hi> God reſted one day in ſeven, therefore you muſt alſo ſo reſt. It is impoſſible we ſhould reſt that day in which God reſted, that day
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109812:16"/> vaniſhed, and returned no more: Our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren therefore can plead only for the ſeventh in the weekly Revolution, and why not fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a ſeventh in Number only, not in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But we may freely grant our Brethren that that argument held for the ſeventh i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> order ſo far as it could be, without any damage to our cauſe. The Precept is on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thing, the argument is another.</p>
               <p>It doth not at all follow, that becauſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> force of the Precept is perpetual, therefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the force of every argument ſhould be ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alſo. One argument brought hath a per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>petual force, <hi>Gods allowing us ſix dayes ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> our own imployment:</hi> what if the other ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a temporary force, a force only for tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> time, during which the Sabbath then inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted was to continue? There is nothing more ordinary in Holy Writ, than to annex arguments of an univerſal, eternal force to Precepts, that were to expire; and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of a temporary particular vertue to Precepts that obliged for ever. How often do we find this as an Argument affixed t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Ceremonial, and Judicial Laws, confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by all to oblige only the <hi>Jewes, For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> am the Lord thy God?</hi> To give but one in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtance,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109812:16"/> 
                  <hi>Lev.</hi> 22, 29, 30. The Precept relates <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o a ſacrifice of Thanksgiving;</hi> it injoyned them <hi>to eat it all the ſame day, to leave none of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t till the morning,</hi> for ſaith God, <hi>I am the Lord,</hi> God is all our Lord, yet we are not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll bound to that Sacrifice, or the rites rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ting to it.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide: The Argument affixed to the firſt Commandement is, <hi>I am the Lord thy God, which brought thee out of the Land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>out of the houſe of bondage.</hi> The command, in the next words, <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods but me,</hi> concerns us as well as the <hi>Jews,</hi> but the argument from the <hi>deliverance from Egypt</hi> and the <hi>houſe of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage</hi> literally only concern'd them. So here; The Precept, <hi>Remember to keep holy the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath Day;</hi> with the direction, and firſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, in thoſe words, <hi>Six dayes ſhalt thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, and do all that thou haſt to doe, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he ſeventh day is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God,</hi> &amp;c. concerns all:</p>
               <p>But the other Argument, in thoſe words,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For in ſix dayes the Lord made Heaven and Earth, the Sea, and all that in them is, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſted the ſeventh day, wherefore the Lord bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſeventh day and hallowed it.</hi> We ſay, only concerned the proportion of time: not
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:109812:17"/> inforcing the ſame day in order: or if it did, had but a temporary force (that day being then under divine inſtitution) and there being a need of that argument to quicken the <hi>Jews</hi> to obſerve it, for thoſe many years it was (confeſſedly) to continue after the giving of the Law in <hi>Sinai.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor indeed was it poſſible for all the World, or for the <hi>Jews</hi> in ſucceſſive times to keep the juſt ſeventh part of time from the Creation, in a ſtrict computation; thoſe who know any thing, know how this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation was interrupted in <hi>Joſhuah</hi> and <hi>Hezekiahs time,</hi> and what a difference there is betwixt dayes in ſeveral climates and quarters of the World; making it a thing impoſſible, either for all people (and the Precept concerns all) or for the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> people (afterwards diſperſed over all the world) to keep the punctual ſeventh day in order from the Creation, according to a weekly revolution. I conclude therefore, that there is no pretence from the fourth Commandment, for any to urge that we more glorifie God by obeying his will in the obſervation of the laſt than of the firſt day of the week, yea it will anon appear, we leſs obey God. The fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:109812:17"/> only requiring one intire day of ſeven, and ſuch a one as God had or ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point. If we prove God hath appointed another, the fourth Commandment ſtands good, and we are rebellious againſt God if we inſiſt on the old Sabbath, and neglect what God hath more lately appointed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> That the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, was Lord of the Sabbath: and had a power as to alter all Laws relating to the acts of Worſhip, ſo this Law relating to the ſolemn time of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</head>
               <p>I Cannot but be ſo far charitable to our Brethren ingaged againſt us in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, as to believe they will yield us what we have hitherto contended for; ſo far as it extends only to a liberty for the Lord of Heaven and Earth, after his giving the fourth Commandement, to alter it, for though we cannot aſſert ſuch a liberty, no not to the Eternal God, as to ſuch things, in the ten Commandments, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in them a morall goodneſs, antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daneous
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:109812:18"/> to the Precept, (being made ſo by the Eternall will of God,) and the things being of that nature, that the contrary to them muſt neceſſarily impeach the glory of God, (which he cannot with conſiſtency to his holy nature recede from) yet for ſuch things, whoſe goodneſs meerly depends upon the Precept, certainly without dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to the Soveraign authority of God, we muſt acknowledge a power reſerved unto God to make an alteration of them: So that though we cannot ſuppoſe that God ſhould by any Precept, ſucceſſive to the morall Law, give his creatures liberty not to glorifie him, or to blaſpheme him, or to have any other gods beſides him; yet we muſt acknowledge a liberty to God, if he pleaſed to alter the law for the time of his Worſhip, that being a thing from which no glory further ariſeth to God, than as his will is obeyed. Now I preſume it a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple agreed betwixt us, and our Brethren, That <hi>Jeſus Chriſt is God over all bleſſed for ever, the brightneſs of his Fathers Glory, the expreſs image of his perſon</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh) And that in purſuance of an Eternal Covenant he was in the fulneſs of time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nt into the world, not only to <hi>work</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:109812:18"/> out mans redemption, by his <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>paſſive</hi> obedience to the Law; But alſo (as the firſt Miniſter of the Goſpel) as the <hi>head</hi> and Law-giver of the Goſpel Church) to reveal his Fathers will for the Worſhip of God in it; to this purpoſe he tells us, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.27. <hi>That all things were delivered him by the Father.</hi> Accordingly, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. he inſtituteth the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> and in <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18. he inſtituteth the <hi>Miniſtry, preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpel,</hi> and <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> and <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.20. he authorizeth his Apoſtles <hi>to teach whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he had commanded them.</hi> And leſt we ſhould think that although the alteration of the Acts of Worſhip were within Chriſts commiſſion: yet the alteration of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn time of Worſhip was not, he hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired three of the four Evangeliſts to tell us, what he aſſerted, that he was <hi>Lord of the Sabbath, Matth.</hi> 12.8. <hi>Mar.</hi> 2.28. <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.5. Texts which I wonder Mr. <hi>Titham</hi> ſhould fancy to have any thing in them for the old Sabbath. For he who reads any of the Evangeliſts muſt yield the ſenſe to be this at firſt ſight: That he had authority to expound the Law of the Sabbath, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the rigid ſenſe of the Doctors of thoſe times, ſo as it ſhould allow a liberty
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109812:19"/> for acts of <hi>neceſſity, piety,</hi> and <hi>mercy.</hi> The words do plainly aſſert our Saviour an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to alter the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> for he is <hi>Lord of it.</hi> Our Brethren by their daily practice, yield our Saviour a liberty to alter the <hi>Acts of Worſhip;</hi> hence they do not offer Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, as the <hi>Jews</hi> did (though by the way obſerve, our Saviour never ſaid to us, <hi>You ſhall no longer Sacrifice</hi>) they allow of <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme</hi> inſtead of <hi>Circumciſion;</hi> though it be worthy of our Brethrens obſervation, that Mr. <hi>Titham</hi> and Mr. <hi>Pooly</hi> fell to Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and conſequently to a denyall of Chriſt, and under the terror of that Text, <hi>If you be circumciſed Chriſt ſhall profit you nothing.</hi> Our Brethren alſo allow the Ordinances of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> and <hi>Preaching:</hi> and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it is very unreaſonable for our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to allow their Lord and Saviour the authority to alter the Acts of Worſhip, and to deny him a power as to the time of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Certainly, the time is not ſo conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable as to the glory of God, as the Acts of Worſhip are; beſides that (as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) to deny our Saviour this Authority, is to deny him to be God Equall with his Father, and to deny what three of the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts expreſly aſſert with an <hi>even</hi> and <hi>alſo:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:109812:19"/> The Son of Man is Lord</hi> even <hi>or</hi> alſo <hi>of the Sabbath day.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> That the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in purſuance of his Commiſſion, for eſtabliſhing the Goſpel Church, did alter the Sabbath, from the ſeventh to the firſt day of the Week. How this appears.</head>
               <p>THis being obtained, we have nothing to doe, but to prove, <hi>That our Lord did alter the Sabbath day.</hi> In or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to which proof,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sheppard,</hi> Theſ. Sab. th. <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> what that holy and learned man Mr. <hi>Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard</hi> hath ſaid, is to be obſerved.</p>
               <q>We are not to expect ſuch evidence from Scripture, concerning this change, as fond and humorous wits ſometimes plead for in this controverſie: Namely, that Chriſt ſhould come, with Drum and Trumpet as it were upon Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> and proclaim by word, or writing, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs words. The <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Sabbath is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogated, and the firſt day of the week in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted in its room, to be obſerved of all
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:109812:20"/> Chriſtians to the end of the world; For it is not the Lords manner to ſpeak ſo in many things concerning his Kingdom, but as it were occaſionally, or in way of hiſtory, or Epiſtle to ſome particular Church or people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>The Scripture ſaith, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> after his reſurrection <hi>continued upon the Earth forty dayes, ſpeaking of things concerning the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God,</hi> Acts 1.3. and St. <hi>John,</hi> chap. 21. tells us, that all things which he ſaid, <hi>were not written, for the World would not have held the books.</hi> Indeed it is not expreſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid, that in that time he inſtructed them, as to the change of the Sabbath, as it is not ſaid, he any time ſpake to them about the ceaſing of <hi>Circumciſion, Sacrifices,</hi> the <hi>Paſchall Lamb,</hi> &amp;c. nor is it ſaid what in particular he taught them within thoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty dayes: But certainly a moderate degree of charity will inforce us to believe, that what we ſhall find in Holy Writ, the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> and <hi>primitive Churches</hi> exemplarily pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing in this thing, they learned either by <hi>word of mouth,</hi> or by <hi>infallible inſpiration</hi> from their Lord and Maſter, (which is all one to us) and we muſt be very unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:109812:20"/> to think that thoſe firſt, and greateſt Miniſters of the Goſpel (the greateſt Light ever ſet upon the Lords Hill) ſhould by word of mouth or practice teach the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians ſo weighty a thing as the <hi>change of the Sabbath,</hi> without any direction or authority from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. The Apoſtles in what they did were fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of Chriſt Jeſus, and upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1. the Apoſtle calls to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to be <hi>followers of him,</hi> and Phil. 4.9. <hi>Thoſe things which you have learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and heard, and ſeen in me, do ye.</hi> It is true, the Examples of the Apoſtles are not in all things, our rules, nor by us to be imitated. <hi>But in thoſe things which they did not upon ſome ſpecial reaſon, and wherein we can imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate them, unqueſtionably they are to be imitated;</hi> and that in force of many Scriptures ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that purpoſe: And in ſuch things their example unqueſtionably amounts to a divine Inſtitution. What have we more than the example of the Apoſtolical Churches practice for our uſe of <hi>Water in Baptiſme, adminiſtring the Lords Supper to Women,</hi> &amp;c. So that the buſineſs in queſtion will much lye upon theſe two things: Whether we can ſhew <hi>any Inſtitution of Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>practice</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:109812:21"/> of the <hi>Apoſtolical Churches</hi> in this caſe?</p>
               <p>Here we will alſo freely grant our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, <hi>That the exerciſe of holy dutyes on a day will not argue ſuch a day was obſerved as a Sabbath:</hi> But if we will prove, that the firſt day of the week was by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Church, obſerved as the Chriſtian Sabbath, we muſt prove,
<q>That Day ſet apart for Sabbath Services, more than any other day in the Week, and honoured above any other day for that end.</q>
               </p>
               <p>To this purpoſe there have been three more eminent Texts in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment inſiſted on, almoſt by all Divines who have handled this controverſie, I ſhall not pretend to add any thing much conſiderable, to what hath been largely and learnedly ſaid by Dr. <hi>Young,</hi> Mr. <hi>Caudry,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sheppard,</hi> Mr. <hi>Warren, &amp;c.</hi> but I ſhall gather what they have ſaid into fewer words, and give it my Brethren in their own tongue, and it may be more in their own dialect, in a plain and familiar ſtyle; for I write not to Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and ſo am under no temptation to ſhew reading or Rhetorick; nor am I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged with any particular Adverſary, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:109812:21"/> ſo not concerned to digreſs to anſwer all his impertinencies.</p>
               <p>The firſt Text I find inſiſted on is, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.7. where we read, that the Apoſtle ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſailed from <hi>Philippi</hi> to <hi>Troas,</hi> abode there <hi>ſeven dayes. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the firſt day of the week</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>when the Diſciples came together to break Bread,</hi> Paul <hi>preached unto them ready to depart on the morrow, and continued his ſpeech untill Midnight. And there was many lights in the upper Chamber where they were gathered together.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. It is firſt very obſervable, That the Holy Ghoſt tells us, that <hi>Paul abode at Troas ſeven dayes,</hi> one of which muſt needs be the Jewiſh Sabbath. It is not unlikely, that the Apoſtle prayed, and preached amongſt them more than once; but here's no notice taken of any meetings of the Chriſtians, any day; or of any Religious duties per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by St. <hi>Paul</hi> any day but upon the <hi>ſeventh day</hi> after he came there, (which the Apoſtle tells us was the <hi>firſt day of the week</hi>) ſo that there is an eſpecial notice taken of this day by the Holy Ghoſt, of the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore none at all in this place, amongſt a company of Chriſtians: <hi>Paul</hi> was there <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven dayes,</hi> it is not ſaid that he reſted, or
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:109812:22"/> went into the Jewiſh Synagogue on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sabbath (probably there was none there,) but the ſixth day of <hi>Pauls</hi> abode there i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reckoned as an ordinary day at <hi>Troas,</hi> yet that muſt be the Jewiſh Sabbath, no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any preparation to it, any ſolemn dutyes in it, it is counted amongſt the other week-dayes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, If here had been no more notice taken of the <hi>Lords day,</hi> the <hi>firſt day of the Week</hi> than of the day before, we could have had no argument from hence; but it is expreſſely ſaid, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the firſt day of the week, when the Diſciples came together to break bread,</hi> &amp;c. where many things are to be noted.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The Name.</hi> The firſt day of the week, not <hi>one day in the week</hi> (as ſome would have it.) It is the ſame phraſe, <hi>Job.</hi> 20.1. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.1. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.2. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24. 1. Certainly, the Evangeliſts deſign was not to tell us, that our Lord roſe <hi>one day of the week,</hi> but <hi>the day next to the Jewiſh Sabbath,</hi> which was the laſt day of the week. If (as ſome have contended,) the word ſhould be tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>One day of the week;</hi> it would agree with no other uſe of the phraſe in Holy Writ. 2. <hi>It would not tell us when they met,</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:109812:22"/> which plainly is the Holy Ghoſts deſign. Were it reaſonable to tranſlate, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.1, 2. <hi>And when the Sabbath was paſt, very early in the morning, one day of the week, they came,</hi> &amp;c. is it not plainly the Evangeliſts deſign to tell us what time they came, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſaith, 1. <hi>When the Sabbath was paſt,</hi> 2. <hi>Early in the morning.</hi> 3. <hi>The firſt day of the week.</hi> It is a manner of ſpeaking accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> who ordinarily (for want of ſuch a plenty of words as other Languages have) expreſs the <hi>cardinall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> by the <hi>Ordinall numerall.</hi> So <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.5. The evening and the morning were <hi>One day,</hi> (ſo it is in the Hebrew) that is the <hi>firſt day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It is not ſaid, <hi>Paul called them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> or that the Church called a meeting that day, but <hi>when the Diſciples met together,</hi> or (they being gathered together (for in the Greek it is the <hi>Genitive</hi> caſe put abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute,) the Text mentions it as a time when of courſe, and according to their cuſtom they were met together.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is not ſaid, <hi>when ſome of the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples were met together,</hi> but [the Diſciples be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gathered together] that is, the Church being met, as publickly as thoſe times would
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:109812:23"/> bear, <hi>they came together,</hi> v. 7. <hi>They were ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together,</hi> v. 8. <hi>there were many lights in the room where they were gathered,</hi> v. 8. Here are words enough to conclude a <hi>Church-meeting,</hi> a <hi>numerous meeting,</hi> ſuch a one as required many lights, and put <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichus</hi> to take his ſeat in a dangerous win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Text ſaith, <hi>they were met together to break bread.</hi> A phraſe indeed which doth not alwayes ſignifie, <hi>receiving the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> but very ordinarily: It is further ſaid, that <hi>Paul preached,</hi> and <hi>continued his ſpeech till midnight.</hi> The end of their meeting was <hi>ſolemn, religious dutyes,</hi> in a <hi>Church-aſſembly,</hi> and they accordingly were performed till Midnight.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It is not ſaid they were <hi>gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the evening,</hi> but <hi>upon the firſt day of the week,</hi> though the duties were held on till midnight; therefore it is but a fancy of them who think it was evening before they met.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Paul</hi> did preach amongſt them upon other dayes, and the Lords Supper were adminiſtred any of the other dayes: Yet the Holy Ghoſt's taking no notice of thoſe performances, but only of what was done
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:109812:23"/> in this day, is no mean argument, that this was the day, which he would have us take notice of, as the ſolemn time for Chriſtians Goſpel-worſhip, in imitation of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical preſident.</p>
               <p>I am not ignorant what pains ſome have taken to avoid the dint of this Text. Mr. <hi>Brabourn</hi> and Mr. <hi>Titham,</hi> both tell us, <hi>the Meeting was but occaſional and extraordinary;</hi> for which there had been ſome colour, if the Text had ſaid, That <hi>Paul</hi> called <hi>them together;</hi> or <hi>that they were called together:</hi> but it ſaith, they <hi>being met together,</hi> ſpeaking of it plainly, as an ordinary, cuſtomary day when they were wont to meet: But, ſaith Mr. <hi>Titham,</hi> As ſoon as they were met, <hi>lights were ſeen in the upper Chamber,</hi> ſo that (he ſayes) tis not probable <hi>they met till towards evening.</hi> But the Scripture ſaith no ſuch thing; it ſaith they were met <hi>on the firſt day of the week;</hi> and <hi>Paul continued his ſpeech till midnight,</hi> when he began it, it ſaith not, but the term <hi>continued,</hi> implieth he began long before: Mr. <hi>Brabourn</hi> thinks it proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, they did not <hi>begin to meet till toward evening, becauſe that was the time for the Lords Supper, according to our Saviours example,</hi> Mar. 14 17. <hi>and the example of the Primitive
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:109812:24"/> Church:</hi> 1 Cor. 11.21. That our Saviour firſt celebrated the Lords Supper in the Evening was plainly upon a ſpecial reaſon, that being the inſtituted time for the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over; in the cloſe of which he deſigned the inſtitution of the Supper; but that either <hi>we</hi> are ſtill obliged to that hour, or that the Apoſtles kept them to that hour, is very hard to prove. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> uſed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.21. will not do it: It is tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Feaſt, Mat.</hi> 23.6. <hi>Mar.</hi> 12.39. <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.46. and indifferently ſignifies <hi>Breakfaſt, Dinner</hi> or <hi>Supper,</hi> as might be ſhewed from many <hi>Authors.</hi> Mr. <hi>Titham</hi> ſayes, the Lords Supper was not adminiſtred till the next day, for <hi>Paul continued his ſpeech till midnight,</hi> and after this he reſtored <hi>Eutychus,</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 11. <hi>when he was come up again, and had broken bread, and eaten, and talkt a long while, even till break of day, he departed.</hi> But it is ſaid, <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the firſt day of the week, when the Diſciples came together to break bread.</hi> So as plainly, their deſigned meeting to break bread was upon the firſt day ot the week. I clearly think, the ſecond <hi>breaking of bread, v.</hi> 11. was not any <hi>religious duty,</hi> but a <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily refreſhment Paul took before his journey,</hi> the phraſe is ſo uſed, beſides, the manner
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:109812:24"/> of the phraſe methinks in this place plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enough ſignifieth it; <hi>When he had bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken bread, and eaten, and talkt with them.</hi> When all the Religious duties of the day were over, and <hi>Paul had refreſhed himſelf</hi> with ſome Victuals, and diſcourſed with his friends, he took his journey. The ſenſe of the Text is plainly this: <hi>Paul</hi> religiouſly with them kept the firſt day of the Week, <hi>preaching, adminiſtring the Lords Supper;</hi> and he being to leave them preached ſomething longer than uſually; <hi>Eutichus</hi> falls aſleep, falls from the window where he was, and was taken up dead. <hi>Paul</hi> (the duties being done) recovers him to life again, refreſheth himſelf with Victuals, and diſcourſeth with them till break of the day, and then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth. Laſtly, Mr. <hi>Titham</hi> is miſtaken, to ſay, St. <hi>Pauls</hi> once preaching at <hi>Troas</hi> is <hi>ſo ſtood upon</hi> as canonizing a Sabbath: That which is inſiſted upon, is this: <hi>That</hi> Paul <hi>ſtaying at</hi> Troas <hi>ſeven dayes, no mention is made of the Chriſtians there meeting together any other day, but on the firſt day of the week, upon which it is evident that they met, and met on purpoſe for the moſt ſolemn Goſpel-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, and brake not up from them till mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night: yea, and the Holy Ghoſt mentions their
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:109812:25"/> meeting that day as an uſual cuſtomary thing</hi> Mr. <hi>Brabourn</hi> puts us to too hard a task to prove that they abſtained from their ſervile labour: We hope our Brethren will not think that they were at their ſervile labour whiles <hi>Paul</hi> was preaching, or while they were me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> together to partake of the Lords Supper. And it is not very charitable for us to think (if they had not kept this day as the Chriſtian Sabbath) that ſo near a ſolemn ſervice which requireth preparation, they ſhould be diſtracting themſelves with ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar labour. Beſides that, this will fall as heavy upon our brethren, What one Text have our Brethren to prove that <hi>Paul</hi> or any Chriſtians abſtained from all <hi>ſervile la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour</hi> on the <hi>ſeventh day,</hi> which was the Jewiſh <hi>Sabbath,</hi> or that they <hi>kept it?</hi> It is indeed ſaid, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.14, 15. That <hi>Paul</hi> coming to <hi>Antioch,</hi> went into <hi>the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, and ſate down: and after the reading of the Law, and the Prophets,</hi> upon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the Rulers of the Synagogue, <hi>Paul</hi> preacht a notable <hi>Goſpel-ſermon</hi> to them, to convince them of their errors. V. 42. <hi>The Gentiles deſired that thoſe words might be preached to them;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, we tranſlate it <hi>the next Sabbath;</hi> and I muſt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:109812:25"/> ingenuouſly confeſs, that if that tranſlation were neceſſary, it would have more colour for an argument on our Brethrens ſide, than any place I know in Scripture will afford them, that the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> when the <hi>Jews</hi> were gone, ſhould pitch upon the next Sabbath above other dayes to hear <hi>Paul</hi> again. But as there is no neceſſity to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late it ſo, ſo neither is that tranſlation of the particle I think to be juſtified by any like uſage of it: We tranſlate it, <hi>Between</hi> generally. See <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.15. <hi>Between thee and him alone,</hi> Matth. 23 35. Luk. 11.51. <hi>Between the Temple and the Altar,</hi> Luk. 16.26. <hi>There is a gulf between me and thee.</hi> Joh. 4.26. <hi>In the mean while,</hi> that is, <hi>in the time between,</hi> Acts 12.6. <hi>Peter was ſleeping between two Souldiers,</hi> Acts 15.9. <hi>betwixt us and them.</hi> Rom. 2.15. <hi>Their thoughts in the mean while,</hi> or [between themſelves as it is in the <hi>Margent</hi>] So as to this very Text. The Margent tells you, it may be read; <hi>In the week between,</hi> or in the <hi>Sabbath between:</hi> If our Brethren will allow the latter which is juſtifiable, there was a <hi>Sabbath between</hi> that and the next <hi>Jewiſh Sabbath;</hi> which muſt be the Chriſtian Sabbath, but if they take it in the former ſenſe, the <hi>Gentiles</hi> did
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:109812:26"/> not deſire <hi>Paul</hi> to preach the next <hi>ſevent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> day</hi> thoſe words, but <hi>in the week between,</hi> ſo the words are: And the <hi>Margent</hi> of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Bibles tell us, the Tranſlators ſaw thus it might be read, nor could any thing lead them to this tranſlation, but <hi>v.</hi> 44. where it is ſaid, that the next <hi>Sabbath day came almoſt the whole City together to hear the word of the Lord;</hi> which they might do, yet that not the day which the <hi>Gentiles</hi> before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned deſired, to hear the ſame things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. <hi>Acts</hi> 16. <hi>Paul</hi> comes to <hi>Derbe,</hi> and <hi>Lyſtra,</hi> quarters very full of <hi>Jewes,</hi> for the Text ſaith, for that very reaſon, <hi>Paul cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed Timothy, though his Father was a Greek, v.</hi> 3. Thence they go to <hi>Philippi,</hi> there <hi>v.</hi> 13. It is ſaid, that on the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day they <hi>went out of the City by the River ſide, where Prayer was wont to be made.</hi> It is not indeed ſaid it was by the <hi>Jews;</hi> but <hi>Lydia</hi> is called one that <hi>worſhipped God:</hi> who but <hi>Jewes</hi> in <hi>Macedonia</hi> ſhould worſhip God at that time, I cannot tell; for we never read before that the Goſpel was preached in thoſe parts. Whereas Mr. <hi>Brabourn</hi> objects, ſo it is ſaid, <hi>Cornelius,</hi> Acts 10 2. <hi>was one who feared God with all his houſe:</hi> it is true, but he lived in <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> a place not ſo far
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:109812:26"/> from <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> (where the Apoſtles had ſo abundantly preacht the Goſpel) as <hi>Philippi</hi> in <hi>Macedonia</hi> was, and therefore far more likely to be a <hi>Gentile Proſelyte</hi> than <hi>Lydia</hi> was, but at once to anſwer this objection of the Apoſtles going into the Jewiſh Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues, and preaching on their Sabbath day either there, or elſewhere where they were met.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>It is moſt evident, that the Lord indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Chriſtians a time, to be ſatisfied, that thoſe things in this Rule of Worſhip given to the Jews which were ceremonial, and tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, had an end, during which time, it was lawfull for them to obſerve them.</hi> Though they all died with Chriſt, yet the Lord al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them (having his own ancient In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution) a time for honourable Burial. Hence, <hi>Acts</hi> 16. Paul <hi>circumciſed Timothy,</hi> as well as <hi>kept the Sabbath day,</hi> and in the firſt Councel the Apoſtles injoyn'd the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> to abſtain from <hi>blood</hi> and <hi>things ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled,</hi> and <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.6. <hi>gives a liberty to the Chriſtian,</hi> to obſerve the Jewiſh dayes. This liberty did not laſt long, for the Apoſtle tells the <hi>Galatians, Acts</hi> 15.2. That if they <hi>were circumciſed, Chriſt ſhould profit them no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi> And in this very point of dayes,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:109812:27"/> 
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.13. he tells them that <hi>he was afraid of them, becauſe they obſerved dayes, and months, and years:</hi> It is manifeſt this Epiſtle to the <hi>Galathians</hi> was one of his laſt, it was written from <hi>Rome,</hi> where (as he tells us) he was then in bonds, and as judicious Interpreters think, not above two year before his death, which was about 65 years after our Saviour. That to the <hi>Romans</hi> was wrote long before, ſo was his circumciſing <hi>Timothy,</hi> Acts 16. If therefore the Apoſtle did for a time allow the <hi>Jewes</hi> their <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> and go and preach amongſt them on that day, it was not ſo much, as his cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſing <hi>Timothy;</hi> which yet he did, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the will of God for indulging his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples weakneſs for a time. Nor yet is it needfull that we ſhould ſay the <hi>Jewiſh Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi> was a <hi>Ceremony,</hi> we ſay the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> that is one day in ſeven was <hi>Originally morall,</hi> but the keeping of the ſeventh from the Creation, but a <hi>temporary Ordinance for the Jewes,</hi> therefore <hi>Deut.</hi> 15. God ſaith, <hi>And Remember, that thou wert a ſervant in the land of Egypt, and that the Lord brought thee ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thence, through a mighty hand, and by a ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out arm: therefore the Lord thy God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded thee to keep the Sabbath day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:109812:27"/>2. We ſay, <hi>Pauls going into the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, or preaching on that day, doth not prove that he or the Chriſtians with him, had any conſcience, or reverence for that day more than another, they doubtleſs prayed, and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed other dayes.</hi> 'Tis no where ſaid, they kept or obſerved the <hi>Sabbath day;</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> would come together no other day, at leaſt in no ſuch numbers: Prudence taught this great Fiſherman, to throw his Net where he ſaw moſt Fiſh; and <hi>Paul</hi> had a great zeal and kindneſs for his Brethren the <hi>Jews,</hi> as appears from <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.1, 2, 3. they might indeed have had <hi>hearers</hi> other dayes, but probably <hi>no Jews,</hi> (unleſs proſelyted) at leaſt no ſuch numbers as on their <hi>Sabbath</hi> day. Mr. <hi>Brabourn</hi> talks idly, to tell us of <hi>Pauls</hi> calling <hi>Jews</hi> together at <hi>Rome,</hi> being their Countreyman, and a meer ſtranger as to his Doctrine, but <hi>v.</hi> 29. they quickly <hi>went away:</hi> And for the Jews <hi>Acts</hi> 19. that <hi>came to hear him,</hi> they were apparently ſuch as the Goſpel had wrought upon: but it is plain, that the Jews, who ſtill kept their Judaical Principles, and knew any thing of <hi>Paul</hi> after his converſion, were not likely to meet together upon his invitation. So that our brethrens argument for the <hi>ſeventh
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:109812:28"/> day Sabbath,</hi> from St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s and others of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and Primitive Diſciples, going into the Synagogues, or to other places where they were wont to meet, upon that day; is no better argument than ſome bring for our Saviours <hi>approbation</hi> of the Jewiſh <hi>Feaſt of Dedication</hi> (of no Divine Inſtitution, or at leaſt ſo ſuppoſed) becauſe he was <hi>that day</hi> found <hi>walking</hi> in <hi>Solomons Porch,</hi> waiting for an opportunity in that great concourſe which that day cauſed, to preach the Goſpel; or than it would be for a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Miniſter at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> (if he had leave) on <hi>Friday</hi> (their Sabbath) to goe and preach the Goſpel. That therefore he obſerved the <hi>Saracens</hi> Feſtivall. In very deed an argument of no force at all to any ſober, judicious, and deliberate Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, It is worthy of all our obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that although we read, that for ſo long time as the Apoſtles had any hopes of gaining the Jews, and therefore kept a communion with their Church, he did take advantage of their Sabbath to preach the Goſpel, it being as indifferent for him to do it on that day as on any other: yet after that the Apoſtle had made a perfect <hi>ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> from the <hi>Jewiſh Church,</hi> of which we
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:109812:28"/> read, Acts 19.9. <hi>when divers were hardned, and believed not, but ſpake evil of that way before the multitude:</hi> he <hi>departed from them, and ſeparated the Diſciples, diſputing daily in the School of one Tyrannus,</hi> though <hi>this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued for the ſpace of two years,</hi> v. 10. yet we never read of any preaching by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles on that day, or any thing making the leaſt ſhew of their obſervation of it. The time of indulgence was now out. The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians were now ſettled in a diſtinct Church by themſelves, and now they keep only to Goſpel Inſtitutions; there was no more hope of <hi>Pauls becoming all things to the Jews,</hi> to gain ſome of them. So that no inſtance can be given of any meeting of Chriſtians meerly for performance of Religious dutyes upon the <hi>ſeventh day</hi> (which our Brethren do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for) ſo that our Brethren in this point are without any one Scriptural Preſident for a <hi>Chriſtian meeting</hi> on their ſeventh day: Examples of mixed meetings (whiles the <hi>Jews</hi> were moſt numerous in places, and had their Synagogues) indeed they have. But an example of a pure Chriſtian meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they have none; but in the very next Chapter, after the aforeſaid ſeparation, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. we have, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.7. of Chriſtians met
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:109812:29"/> 
                  <hi>on the firſt day of the week</hi> on purpoſe for religious duties.</p>
               <p>It is very true (if we may believe other writings not of divine authority, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly an humane faith may be allowed them) we do find, that after the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles age, the Chriſtians in ſome Churches did meet on the <hi>Jewiſh ſabbath</hi> and perform ſome religious duties, but putting a vaſt difference between that, and the <hi>Lords day.</hi> As Dr. <hi>Young</hi> hath noted.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It was not a <hi>cuſtom in all Churches</hi> particularly not in that of <hi>Rome, or Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi> ſaith <hi>Sozomen, Athanaſius,</hi> and <hi>Turtullian</hi> (both great lights in their times) tell us they obſerved it not. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> condemns the <hi>Nazarites,</hi> and <hi>Ebionites,</hi> for Hereticks, for their obſervation of it. But in all Churches the <hi>Lords day</hi> was obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, thoſe that in any degree kept the other day, were the <hi>Eaſtern Churches,</hi> among whom the <hi>Jews</hi> were moſt, <hi>the vail before whoſe eyes,</hi> a little for a time hindred the Chriſtians ſeeing ſo well as they might, and ought.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Neither did they obſerve any <hi>ſeventh day,</hi> but made <hi>Canons</hi> for omiſſion of ſome, but they never diſpenſed with the obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Lords day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:109812:29"/>3. Nor did they on that day <hi>perform all religious duties;</hi> they indeed, <hi>read the word, prayed,</hi> and <hi>preached</hi> ſometimes, but never ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred <hi>the Lords ſupper on that day.</hi> If we may believe <hi>Athanaſius, Auſtine, Socrates</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> quoted all by the Learned Dr. <hi>Young</hi> in this caſe, on his book called <hi>Dies Dominica.</hi> Chap. 3.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They <hi>left people at liberty to meet, or not to meet on that day,</hi> as we do on lecture dayes. But injoyning the obſervation of the Lords day, without indulging any liberty for peoples abſence, from the religious ſervices of that day.</p>
               <p n="5">5. They allowed a liberty to labour on the <hi>ſeventh day,</hi> yea <hi>anathematized</hi> thoſe who did not labour but on the <hi>Lords day,</hi> they allowed no labour.</p>
               <p>This, and much more is ſaid by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably learned. Dr. <hi>Young:</hi> whoſe skill in antiquities is ſufficiently known. I have but tranſlated it from him, for the ſake of thoſe who underſtand not Latine.</p>
               <p>Our Brethren therefore (what ever Mr. <hi>Brabourn</hi> ſaith) cannot prove, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ever <hi>kept the ſabbath,</hi> ſo much as once, though they can prove they went into the Synagogues that day, and heard the word
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:109812:30"/> read, and preached: nor ſo much as that they once on that day <hi>received the Lords ſupper</hi> (an ordinance peculiar to Chriſtians.) 2. nor that they did thus in one unmixed aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Chriſtians. 3. Nor that they choſe that day to preach in, only upon deſire from the Jews, did it. 4. Nor that ever <hi>kept the ſabbath,</hi> with Jews and Gentiles to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, much leſs Gentiles alone: though they ſate with them on that day to hear the word read in their ſynagogues, and ſometimes preached themſelves. 5. Nor have they proved that what they did, was not to indulge the weakneſs of the Jews and to gain ſome of them, while the Lords time of indulgence laſted, and Chriſtians newly converted, might underſtand their liberty. 6. Nor yet that they might have got the Jews together on other dayes, which are the things Mr. <hi>Brabourn</hi> (who hath ſpoken in this caſe, and to better purpoſe than any other) glories in. It is true it was <hi>Paul</hi> the Miniſter of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> not <hi>Peter</hi> that did go into the ſynagogues, and preacht ſometimes on the ſeventh day: but it was the ſame <hi>Paul</hi> that <hi>Acts</hi> 16. <hi>becauſe of the Jews in thoſe quarters, circumciſed Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> (as great an enemy as Mr. <hi>B.</hi> would
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:109812:30"/> have us believe him to Ceremonies) For Mr. <hi>Bs.</hi> rule in Divinity, <hi>That actions of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men in ſcripture not contradicted have the force of</hi> a <hi>precept.</hi> I doubt the truth of it, But will freely yield him; <hi>That the Actions of the Apoſtles, poſſible to be done by us, and for which there cannot be a particular reaſon given why they ſhould not alledge, or for which there cannot be a reaſon given, why the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles at that time did them, which reaſon will not now hold, have the force of a precept.</hi> But we alledge a particular reaſon, <hi>viz.</hi> to avoid the offence of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and to gain ſome of them, we have no cauſe now of fear for the one: nor hope for the other. In the mean time Mr. <hi>B.</hi> and we are agreed in his other rule. <hi>That actions of the holy Apoſtles in Scripture, not only not contradicted, but alſo ſuch as in the fourth commandment are commanded, have the force of a precept.</hi> But I have before ſhewed, that the <hi>ſeventh day ſabbath</hi> is no more commanded in the fourth commandment than <hi>ſacrificing</hi> is in the ſecond Commandment. The general is commanded. 1. <hi>A ſabbath.</hi> 2. <hi>A whole day.</hi> 3. <hi>One whole day in ſeven.</hi> 4. <hi>Such a one as God had appointed, or ſhould appoint:</hi> but not that ſeventh day further than it was
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:109812:31"/> then the appointed day, and for ſo long time, as it ſhould ſo continue. But enough is ſaid as to the inforcing of the firſt main text, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.7.</p>
               <p>The ſecond text is that, 1 Cor. 16.1, 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As to the Collection of the Saints, as I have ordained in the Churches of Galatia ſo do you. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the firſt day of the week let every one of you lay by him in ſtore as God hath proſpered him, that there be no gatherings when I come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Many things are obſervable from this text, as light as ſome of our brethren make of it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Here is a <hi>collection</hi> for the <hi>Saints:</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to be againſt the <hi>firſt day of the week,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; the words ſo tranſlated, are the ſame with thoſe, <hi>Mar.</hi> 28.1. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.1. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.7. and do out of queſtion ſignifie that day of the week on which our Lord roſe, therefore they do but miſerably baffle who would tranſlate it <hi>one day of the week.</hi> For it cannot be ſo read in any of the Evangeliſts with out manifeſt injury to the ſenſe. That collecting for the Saints, is a pious, and charitable work fit for the ſabbath, though ſuch a work as may be done on the day (as praying and preaching may) is not to be denied.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:109812:31"/>2. It is not neceſſary we ſhould tranſlate it upon the <hi>firſt day of the week.</hi> It ſignifies as well <hi>againſt the firſt day of the week,</hi> ſo <hi>Mar.</hi> 15.6. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> againſt the feaſt he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed to them one priſoner, that plainly is the ſenſe of the text, for the <hi>Jews</hi> would not come into the Judgement Hall <hi>upon the firſt day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. He doth not only limit the time, but he makes an <hi>ordinance in the caſe,</hi> and that not only for his Church, but for the Churches of <hi>Galatia</hi> alſo. Let any one ſoberly judge whether they can think that the great Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle who was ſo zealous of the <hi>Churches li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty,</hi> and who had ſo particularly declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his zeal to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> Chap. 5. who alſo uſed to deliver unto the Churches <hi>what he had received from the Lord.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. and ſo carefully to diſtinguiſh betwixt things which he adviſed as a man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpecial revelation, and what he ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as given him in charge by his Maſter, as appears in that Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> would have made a Law, binding the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians</hi> conſciences to have their charity ready, <hi>Againſt the firſt day of the week;</hi> If the Lord had not given it him in charge.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Why doth he limit it to the Lords
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:109812:32"/> day? <hi>the firſt day of the week.</hi> But that it was a known day amongſt Chriſtians, when the Church was wont to meet, and they hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before againſt that day laid it <hi>by them in ſtore,</hi> might have a convenient opportunity to bring it with them to the Church meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and deliver it to the <hi>Deacons</hi> as an acceptable goſpel ſacrifice unto the Lord. And when alſo by hearing the word of God preached, and the other ſpiritual du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which that day ſhould be performed, they might have their hearts warmed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that due <hi>chearfulneſs,</hi> and readineſs, which became thoſe who gave unto the Lord.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Laſtly.</hi> I deſire our brethren would ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly conſider, <hi>whether this text doth not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply a ſanctification of that day by ſome former precept of Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</hi> If there were a Law in <hi>England, that there ſhould be a collection for the Saints made in</hi> or <hi>againſt</hi> the <hi>fifth of November;</hi> Would not this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, that that day was a known day, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in reſpect of ſome law, ſetting a mark upon it: or ſome general obſervation of it. But if this were a Church conſtitution, it would yet argue further, and that the Church on that day would meet, and take an account of it. The Apoſtle orders a col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:109812:32"/> for the faints, to be made <hi>in</hi> or <hi>againſt the firſt day of the week.</hi> This cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly argues, a ſpecial remark upon that day, and an uſage for the Church to meet, and and ſo excellently agrees with that <hi>Acts</hi> 20.7. For what Mr. <hi>Tilham</hi> or Mr. <hi>Brabourn</hi> ſaith to weaken this proof, it is of little va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue. Mr. <hi>B.</hi> ſaith that this <hi>order is but for a ſingle action once to be done.</hi> To grant him what he ſaith (though the term may as well be expounded of <hi>every firſt day;</hi> as of one,) eſpecially that <hi>one</hi> being no way notified, but only gueſſed by Mr. <hi>B.</hi> to be the next following the receit of that Epiſtle. For though St. <hi>Paul</hi> would have no gatherings for the <hi>ſtrangers</hi> when he came, yet there might be <hi>collections</hi> for their own. And we know that having collections every Lords day, was in uſe in the primitive Church, after their prayers, whence the prayers were themſelves called <hi>collects:</hi> But (I ſay) to grant this, ſtill the queſtion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, why This collection is ordained to be made <hi>Againſt</hi> or <hi>in the firſt day of the week more than any other:</hi> Whereas both he and Mr. <hi>T.</hi> urge that the text only <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, that every one ſhould lay by himſelf: not that he ſhould give it to the Deacons.</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:109812:33"/> Whence Mr. <hi>Tilham cavils, that if this day had been their ſabbath, the Apoſtle would not have directed a ſurvey of their eſtates how God had proſpered them.</hi> I have ſhewed before the Apoſtle commands <hi>this ſurvey,</hi> and a <hi>laying by</hi> themſelves <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>againſt the firſt day of the week.</hi> We ask why againſt <hi>that day</hi> more than another? but that it was a day when the Church uſed to meet; and they might have an excellent opportunity to bring it in, and have their hearts warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the duties of that day, into a due chearfulneſs becoming them who give unto the Lord. But M. <hi>T.</hi> will not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge a <hi>collection,</hi> a <hi>Lords day,</hi> or a <hi>ſabbath duty.</hi> For then he thinks the Apoſtle would not have added, <hi>that there be no gatherings when I come.</hi> Verily the mans ignorance is to be pitied. Works of <hi>piety, mercy,</hi> and <hi>neceſſity</hi> are doubtleſs <hi>ſabbath duties,</hi> or our Saviour would never have <hi>healed lame</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons on that day. The Apoſtles meaning therefore doubtleſs is, <hi>That there be no ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therings for</hi> theſe <hi>Brethren-ſtrangers</hi> when I come.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>But ſuppoſe it be, yet Mr. <hi>T.</hi> tells us that a ſurvey of their eſtates, (which the Apoſtle doth implicitly command, that
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:109812:33"/> they may ſee how God had proſpered them) was no ſabbath work: But there is no need as I have ſaid we ſhould ſo tranſlate it, nor do I think it the ſenſe, that the <hi>laying aſide</hi> ſhould be <hi>on the firſt day of the week,</hi> but <hi>againſt the firſt day of the week:</hi>
                  </q> Here's no ſurvey of eſtates di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected on that day. In ſhort ſay what we will, our brethren (ſo fond of this noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) will make us believe that the ſtrength of our argument from this text lies, <hi>that we think that the Apoſtle here directed a colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction on the firſt day of the week:</hi> whereas we tell them, that if it were ſo plain as if written with a Sun beam, we do not think that would prove it a <hi>collection</hi> for the ſaints, was a pious and charitable work, but might be done or directed on any day. But this is that we urge from the text. It is plain from holy writ, that the Apoſtles gave a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar honour to this day, more than to any other day of the week. Though on the ſeventh day, the Apoſtles ſo long as the Jewiſh rites were indulged, or ſo long as they had any hopes to convince the Jews, when they came where the Jews had Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, went in, and heard with them, yea, and preached to them. Yet,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:109812:34"/>1. They never met in a perfect Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Chriſtians on that day that we read of: but on the Lords day they did, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.7.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Apoſtle ordains <hi>their goſpel ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> their collection for the poor <hi>Saints at Hieruſalem,</hi> rather againſt this day, than any other.</p>
               <p>But poſſibly we may find that as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, (unqueſtionably by direction from their Lord,) gave more honour to this day than to any other, So our Lord himſelf al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo did ſo.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>This was the day on which he roſe again from the dead.</hi> This I am ſure they will not deny, and verily this is not inconſiderable. Let us but here weigh two or three things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Reſurrection of Chriſt;</hi> was the <hi>Lord Chriſts great work,</hi> by which he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf to be <hi>Lord,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt:</hi> and ſo confirmed the whole goſpel, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he inſtituted in his worſhip. It was that work of his which gave evidence to the vertue both of his life and death. To this end (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>Chriſt both died, and ROSE again, that he might be Lord both of the dead, and of the living. By this he was declared to be the Son of God with
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:109812:34"/> power, Rom.</hi> 1.4. Hence is our <hi>juſtification, Rom.</hi> 4.25. Hence our <hi>peace of conſcience, Rom.</hi> 8.34. Hence our <hi>lively hope,</hi> and the anſwer of a good conſcience, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3.</p>
               <p>It was our great Lords firſt holy-day as I may ſay. Of the day of Chriſts ſuffering he ſaith THIS IS YOUR DAY, <hi>and the power of darkneſs,</hi> a day in which God hath given leave to the Devil and his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments to play their pranks. But this was <hi>His day.</hi> This was the Lord Chriſts <hi>reſt.</hi> The day in which he reſted from the work of Redemption: As his Father had done on the ſeventh day, from the work of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. May we not ſoberly think that our great Lord ſhould, and did chooſe to <hi>lie in his grave</hi> on the ſabbath day, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to let us know, that that <hi>ſabbath</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him, and to riſe the next day, that he might point out unto us, the <hi>new ſabbath,</hi> which he had made for the new <hi>heaven,</hi> and new <hi>earth,</hi> which he had now created on purpoſe to <hi>riſe upon the firſt day,</hi> that his Father by the change of the day might have no loſs as to the time conſecrated by the fourth commandment. Our Lord could have ordered his death ſo as he might have
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:109812:35"/> died, and riſen again on the 2, 3, 4, or 5, days he chooſeth ſo to dye, that he ſhall be buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed during the whole Jewiſh ſabbath: and early in the next morning he ariſeth. Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> us in the next place conſider what he did when he was riſen. The Evangeliſts re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cord, not ſo full a communion of our Lord, with the world, nor with his diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciples, after the reſurrection: for forty day<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he was ſeen of them. In that time (count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the day on which he roſe) were ſeve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſtian ſabbaths, or firſt days of the week. We read only of our Saviours appearing the two firſt of them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>On the day of his reſurrection,</hi> he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth to <hi>Mary Magdalene</hi> looking in the grave for him, and to ſome diſciples <hi>goi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> to Emaus, Luk.</hi> 24.13. and to the <hi>Eleve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> met at <hi>Hieruſalem, Luk.</hi> 24.36. <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and again,</p>
               <p n="2">2. After <hi>eight days</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.26.) We read but of two apparitions more, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one at the Sea of <hi>Tiberias, Joh.</hi> 21. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> other in <hi>Galilee,</hi> which St. <hi>Matthew</hi> litt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more than barely mentions, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.16, 17 We do not think Chriſts appearing made ſabbath, but Chriſts owning his diſciple meetings on theſe dayes, by appearing the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:109812:35"/> to them, ſpeaks <hi>not a little in the caſe,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if it be obſerved that nothing of any worldly diſcourſe is mentioned, as paſſing at theſe times, but our ſaviour at the Sea of <hi>Tiberias,</hi> talks with them in their art freely.</p>
               <p>But ſay our brethren (zealous for the old ſabbath.)</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>If the diſciples of our Saviour, had kept that day as a ſabbath, he or they would not have gone ſuch a journey, as</hi> 60 <hi>furlongs, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt eight miles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Beza</hi> ſaith either <hi>Joſephus</hi> is miſtaken, or ſome error is crept into the copy, for he it is but 30 <hi>furlongs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The length of their <hi>furlongs</hi> we know not. For our Saviour, it was now no la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our to him to move. Certain it is, the way was ſo ſhort as <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.33. <hi>in that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> hour they could return to Hieruſalem</hi> and find the <hi>eleven,</hi> and others gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. We in a time of perſecution oft go as far to hear a ſermon, and yet do not break the ſabbath.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But (they ſay) the text ſaith, Chriſts ſecond appearing was <hi>after eight dayes, Joh.</hi> 20.26. But ſo it is ſaid, that <hi>after three dayes the Son of Man muſt riſe again, Mar.</hi> 8.31.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:109812:36"/>
               <p>Yet we know he roſe on the third day. The <hi>Grecians</hi> had that liberty in their la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>guage of expreſſing themſelves as to expreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a thing as done when once began: Afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>eight dayes</hi> is no more than after the eight day was begun, as after <hi>three dayes</hi> was n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more than after the third day was began</p>
               <p>Our Saviour being now aſcended int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Heaven, we find the diſciples returnin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from mount <hi>Olivet</hi> to <hi>Hieruſalem, Act.</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and read little of them, but of their conti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuing in prayers, and ſupplication, and chooſing an Apoſtle till the day of Pente<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>coſt. What was done in the day of Pente<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>coſt, we find, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. Then the Holy Ghoſt deſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cended, and before that we read of tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deſcending of the Holy Ghoſt the Evange<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſts obſerved; <hi>They were all with one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in one place.</hi> A phraſe fully expreſſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſtian Church-meeting. I am not Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, what a ſtir Mr. <hi>Tilham</hi> keeps, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> prove this was upon the <hi>Jewiſh ſabbath</hi> We ſay with (I think) better evidence, it was upon the Lords day.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It was Gods expreſs law, that the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhould reſt on the <hi>ſeventh day, both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> earing and in harveſt, Exod.</hi> 34.21, 22.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The law for the feaſt of <hi>Pentecoſt</hi> yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:109812:36"/> ſhall find, <hi>Levit.</hi> 23.10, 11, 12, 15, 16. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hen you be come into the land which I ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e you, and ſhall reap the harveſt thereof, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall bring a ſheaf of the firſt fruits of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r harveſt unto the Prieſt, and he ſhall wave <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> together with the offering of a lamb with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> blemiſh, on the morrow after the ſabbath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall wave it. And you ſhall count unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> from the morrow after the ſabbath, from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> day, you brought the ſheafe ſeven ſabbaths <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ill be compleat, even until the morrow after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he ſeventh ſabbath you ſhall number</hi> 50 <hi>dayes.</hi> Deut. 16.9. <hi>Seven weeks ſhalt thou number, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nto thee, begin to number the ſeven weeks him ſuch time as thou beginneſt to put ſickle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>to thy corn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I muſt firſt take notice of a baſe cheat Mr. <hi>Tilham</hi> puts upon his reader,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tilham</hi> 7 day ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath. <hi>p.</hi> 82.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lling them that <hi>Moſes from God appointed Iſrael to bring, on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>orrow after their paſſover ſabbath, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſheaf of their firſt fruits,</hi> &amp;c. (Good reader look into all the texts that mention it, and ſee if God ſayes a word of their <hi>Paſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Sabbath</hi>) but <hi>v.</hi> 11. <hi>The morrow after the ſabbath;</hi> Which was undoubtedly the weekly ſabbath. Beſides, their paſſover ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath was tied to <hi>a day.</hi> It is not to be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:109812:37"/> their corn ſhould alwayes be ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> juſt <hi>that day,</hi> to wit the 14 day of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> firſt moneth. Now they were not to cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>till they had put their ſickle into their cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Deut.</hi> 16.9.</p>
               <p n="1">1. I obſerve firſt it was impoſſible, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Pentecoſt ſhould ever fall upon the Jewiſh ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bath,</hi> for on the <hi>ſabbath day,</hi> they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gods law to reſt. <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.21, 22. <hi>even earing and harveſt.</hi> So the ſooneſt they cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> begin to put their ſickle into their co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt be the firſt day of the week.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They were then to expect till th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>next ſabbath,</hi> and from the morrow afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to count; which makes it neceſſary, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the feaſt of <hi>Pentecoſt</hi> ſhould alwayes fall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>the firſt day of the week.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Here was a <hi>Church-meeting of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans met in one place</hi> on the <hi>firſt day of the wee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Chriſt (who when on the Earth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> we heard, did honour thoſe meetings wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> his own company) <hi>here he ſends the comfor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter;</hi> gives them on this day the <hi>promiſe of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is true Mr. <hi>Ainſworth</hi> and ſome other think the <hi>paſſover ſabbath</hi> was meant: b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> let any one conſider, with reaſon how it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> poſſible, unleſs the corn in <hi>Paleſtina</hi> was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:109812:37"/> ripe before the <hi>fifteenth day of the month Abib,</hi> ſo as they had reaped ſome of it; for till that, there was no beginning to count for <hi>Pentecoſt;</hi> but Mr. <hi>Ainſworth</hi> is far from fathering this (as Mr. <hi>Tilham</hi> doth) on <hi>Moſes,</hi> it was only a notion taken up by that holy man from ſome <hi>Rabbins.</hi> But enough of this; whoſo will read this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from our Saviours Apparitions, and the deſcending of the Holy Ghoſt improved to the height, may have it admirably done by Mr. <hi>Warren,</hi> late Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> in his excellent Book called <hi>The Jewiſh Sabbath antiquated: and the Lords day inſtituted,</hi> from p. 169 to 187. where ſo much is indeed ſaid upon this whole Subject, as I think very little is to be added to it.</p>
               <p>But there is yet behind one Text more, inſiſted on almoſt by all Divines in this caſe; it is that <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.10. <hi>I was in the Spirit on the Lords day, and heard behind me a great voice as of a Trumpet, ſaying, &amp;c.</hi> V. 11. <hi>and I turned to ſee the voice that ſpake with me, and being turned I ſaw ſeven golden Candleſticks, and in the midſt of the ſeven Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſticks one like unto the Son of man,</hi> &amp;c. who is deſcribed further, <hi>v.</hi> 13, 14, 15, 16.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:109812:38"/> where he is ſaid to have <hi>the Stars in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> right hand; and out of his mouth went for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a two-edged ſword.</hi> — Chriſt himſelf opens the Viſion, <hi>v.</hi> 20. — <hi>The ſeven ſtarrs are the Angels of the ſeven Churches: and the ſeven Candleſticks which thou ſaweſt are the ſeven Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>John</hi> at this time was by the <hi>Roman Emperour</hi> baniſhed into the <hi>Iſle of Pathmos</hi> for the Goſpel ſake. Here he ſeeth a <hi>Viſion.</hi> Two things as to the preſent Controverſie are conſiderable in it,
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>What he ſaw.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>When he ſaw it.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>What he ſaw.</hi> He ſaw the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in the middeſt of his Goſpel Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, walking before him in the purity of Goſpel Adminiſtrations, and reaching forth godly Miniſters to them, and furniſhing them with his Word (which is as a <hi>ſharp, two-edged ſword.</hi>) This plainly was the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion interpreted by the Lord himſelf, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.20.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>When ſaw he this?</hi> On the <hi>Lords day:</hi> he was in <hi>the Spirit on the Lords day;</hi> then he heard this voice, then he ſaw this Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:109812:38"/>3. I am aware that this Text hath ſo diſturbed the leaders in this Controverſie oppoſite to us, that they have exerciſed their wits, to find out a <hi>Lords day</hi> not the firſt day of the week. Mr. <hi>Brabourn,</hi> Mr. <hi>Tilham</hi> (and one of more learning and worth than both of them) think it might be the <hi>day of Judgement,</hi> which indeed is called <hi>the day of the Lord,</hi> Phil. 1.16. but never <hi>the Lords day.</hi> Again, the Apoſtle ſpeaks of a <hi>known day,</hi> and of a <hi>day in being</hi> then; but neither of theſe is true of the <hi>day of Judgement,</hi> not yet come, nor to be known <hi>when it ſhall come,</hi> Matth. 24.36. <hi>Of that day and hour knoweth no man.</hi> Others think it might be the day of <hi>Chriſts Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> but it will poſe them to prove that it was then known, or ſo early taken notice of. For thoſe that dream of <hi>Eaſter-day</hi> above an hundred years after this, this was in diſpute when it ſhould be kept.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Tilham</hi> and Mr. <hi>Brabourn</hi> both think (and they do but think ſo) that it was the <hi>ſeventh day;</hi> but why ſhould that be called the <hi>Lords day?</hi> becauſe he that day lay in the Grave think we? God indeed in the Old Teſtament called it his Sabbath, but was it ever ſo called in relation to Chriſt?
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:109812:39"/> did Chriſt ever inſtitute that? Now why the firſt day of the week ſhould be called the <hi>Lords day,</hi> reaſon offers it ſelf plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In oppoſition to his <hi>ſuffering day,</hi> of which he ſaith to his Perſecutors, <hi>This is your day, and the power of darkneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It was the Day when he triumphed over Sin, Death, and Hell.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It was the Day, when he was with power manifeſted to be the Son of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.4.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In all probability <hi>it was the day he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted for the Chriſtian Sabbath:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called the <hi>Lords day,</hi> as the Sacrament is called the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> becauſe he inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Finally, take all the Ancients from <hi>Ignatius</hi> who lived neareſt the Apoſtle downward, they all underſtood by the Lords day, the <hi>firſt day</hi> of the week, and accordingly kept it holy unto the Lord.</p>
               <p>Now let all theſe be laid together, and I beſeech our Brethren, laying aſide al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> partiality, prejudice and ſaction, ſeriouſly to conſider, whether they will not amoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to as good a proof as we have for many other things, that the Lord Chriſt hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:109812:39"/> the Lords day for the Chriſtian Sabbath, though it be not in the Goſpel proclaimed in ſo many words: And in good earneſt I think thoſe of our Brethren who will not judge it ſufficient, if their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences weigh all Goſpel Truths in the ſame ballance, will be in no ſmall danger of being warped in other, and thoſe very weighty Truths of the Goſpel, from a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion in which, the good Lord keep them and us all, for his mercy ſake.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> That the Seventh Day is repealed.</head>
               <p>I Suppoſe I have ſaid enough to juſtifie the diſcharge of the <hi>Old Sabbath.</hi> The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cenſe which the fourth Commandment gives us to labour ſix dayes in the week, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vinceth us under no Obligation to keep more than one Sabbath: Now if the firſt day of the week, (as we have proved) be the Sabbath to be ſanctified, reaſon tells us the Jewiſh Sabbath is diſcharged. Though the Scripture no where ſaith to us, <hi>you ſhall not keep the Paſſeover,</hi> nor <hi>you ſhall not cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe,</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:109812:40"/> yet we underſtand our ſelves diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged of both, by the ſubſtitution of two other Goſpel Sacraments. It is the Lord will (according to the fourth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) we ſhould not be under an obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to keep two dayes in each week; and it is the Lords will, as we have proved, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould keep the firſt day of the week: wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> need we any further witneſs? But yet it be needfull, I think it is not hard t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> evince it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Jewiſh Sabbath (as I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy proved) was never primarily require<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the Morall Law; but only by tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ceremonial or temporary Laws given to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Jews,</hi> which all acknowledge determine by the death of Chriſt, and the extinction of the Jewiſh Polity, and fell of cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> when that fell. The Ordinance for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> particular day of the week was but an O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinance given to hold untill the time <hi>Reformation:</hi> but to add yet a little mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it hath been told our Brethren, and I heart<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly wiſh they would deliberate upon it; Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.5. blameth the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mans,</hi> that amongſt them, <hi>One man eſteem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> one day above another.</hi> Gal. 4.10. he blam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them that <hi>they obſerved dayes,</hi> and <hi>month</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:109812:40"/> and <hi>times,</hi> and <hi>years.</hi> That the Apoſtle, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al. 2.16. cautioneth the Chriſtians, <hi>That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> man ſhould judge them as to meat or drink, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in reſpect of an Holy-day,</hi> or a <hi>New-moon,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Sabbath-day.</hi> That theſe Texts are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be underſtood of the Lords day, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dent,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe (as we have proved) the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es themſelves, and the Chriſtian Churches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en obſerved it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe the fourth Commandment, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d perpetually eſtabliſhed, 1. A Day: 2. A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>venth Day to be ſanctified: Now the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>poſtles words muſt be interpreted ſo as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t to loſe us one of the ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ents.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe to interpret thoſe Texts of all other Jewiſh Holy-dayes, with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion only to the weekly Sabbath, ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> both an unreaſonable interpretation, too ſhort for the terms of the Texts. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonable,</hi> it is an uſual rule, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi lex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> diſtinguit, non eſt diſtinguendum;</hi> we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e no reaſon to diſtinguiſh where the rule <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es no diſtinction, nor can any pretence reaſon be for limiting the ſenſe in that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oner: but to reconcile the Apoſtles Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t with the fourth Commandment, which
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:109812:41"/> may quickly be without ſuch a reſtriction according to what we have proved th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſenſe of it. A <hi>Sabbath</hi> may remain, though <hi>that Sabbath</hi> be aboliſhed. 2. It ſeems alſo too ſhort. The Apoſtle to the <hi>Galatians</hi> uſeth four terms, <hi>Dayes, Months, Times, Years:</hi> Suppoſe by the years be meant th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yearly Feaſt of <hi>Atonement,</hi> or the <hi>years <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Jubile;</hi> by <hi>Moneths,</hi> the <hi>New Moons;</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Times,</hi> their Feaſts of the <hi>Paſſeover, Pentecoſt</hi> &amp;c. ſtill we want an interpretation for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> term <hi>Dayes,</hi> which certainly muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtood of the Jewiſh <hi>ſeventh Dayes,</hi> or <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>baths</hi> returning every week.</p>
               <p n="4">4. What Mr. <hi>Warren</hi> obſerves is alſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſiderable, that all theſe Epiſtles wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wrote to Churches much <hi>leven'd with Ju<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>daiſm;</hi> and under great temptations to it ſo that undoubtedly it was the Apoſtles in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tention by that term to declare the Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtians freedom from the old Sabbath, which alſo as it is plain from <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.15. ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſomething of a Type annexed unto it. Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> enough hath been ſaid to prove the ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Sabbath</hi> out of doors, if not by <hi>repeal,</hi> ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by <hi>expiration,</hi> as being a temporary Ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and by the appointing of anoth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sabbath in the ſtead of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:109812:41"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> To inſiſt upon the old Sabbath is to Judaize, and non-communion our ſelves to all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Churches in the World, both in this and former Ages.</head>
               <p>FRom what hath been ſaid muſt needs follow, that for us now to inſiſt upon the old <hi>Sabbath,</hi> hath a double guilt attending upon it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt is <hi>Judaizing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond is <hi>declining communion with all the Churches of Chriſt</hi> that are or ever were in the world. <hi>Judaizing</hi> ſignifies a tenacious adhering to the Jewiſh Rites, and Cuſtoms, after that Chriſt hath eſtabliſhed <hi>a New Heaven, and a new Earth.</hi> This was the Jews great ſin. It was one piece of our Lords errand into the world, <hi>To change the cuſtoms which Moſes delivered.</hi> A Truth aſſerted by the firſt Chriſtian Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, and for it he was accuſed, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.14. That this was one of thoſe cuſtoms, is plain, if it were not commanded in the fourth Commandment, which we have proved it
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:109812:42"/> was not. Nor doth it hinder that it begun before <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo did <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> and <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion,</hi> yet they were the <hi>Cuſtoms of Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Circumciſion</hi> is ſo called, <hi>Acts</hi> 21.21. He was the firſt who wrote the Laws about them. For any perſon to adhere to any <hi>Iewiſh cuſtom</hi> after Chriſts death, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, is in effect to deny Chriſt to be come in the fleſh. Let me in the bowels of Chriſt, beſeech our Brethren to be ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in this thing: I ſay again, <hi>Whatſoever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to the Worſhip of God, and fell not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly under one of the ten Commandments, and that primarily, nor is eſtabliſhed in the New Teſtament, could be nothing elſe but a piece of Moſes, a Moſaical cuſtom, which Chriſt came on purpoſe to alter;</hi> and to adhere ſtill to them, is to proclaim againſt Heaven, <hi>I have no part in the Son of David.</hi> Hence the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle tells the <hi>Galathians, If they were circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, Chriſt profited them nothing</hi> (that is, thinking themſelves under an obligation to be circumciſed) and again he tells them, <hi>he was afraid of them, leſt he had beſtowed all his labour amongſt them in vain,</hi> preached the Goſpel to them in vain: why? you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve <hi>dayes, and months, and times, and years,</hi> Gal. 4.11. that is, Such Religious dayes as
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:109812:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Jews obſerved according to <hi>Moſes:</hi> I know many of our Brethren will tremble at the apprehenſion of this, I believe many of them have ſaid to the Lord Chriſt, <hi>Thou at my portion,</hi> and that their Souls in truth ſay, <hi>None but Chriſt, None but Chriſt;</hi> and did they know it, would not <hi>deny the Lord that bought them,</hi> or by any action <hi>interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatively</hi> deny, his Authority to alter <hi>the cuſtomes</hi> of <hi>Moſes.</hi> I humbly beg of them, that in tenderneſs to the Lord that bought them, in love to their own Souls, as I truſt they fear every ſin, ſo they would fear their Souls ſinning in this point of Judaizing, which the Apoſtle (as to other points) layes ſo much ſtreſs upon, both in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Galatians,</hi> and <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſsians,</hi> and all along in every Epiſtle. And in a further evidence of this, let me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech our Brethren in all ſeriouſneſs to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, whither the poring upon this notion hath led others, and let them <hi>who yet ſtand, take heed leſt they ſo fall.</hi> There have not been many Leaders in this, opinion known to the World in this latter Age.</p>
               <p>The firſt was <hi>John Thrask;</hi> I never heard that he publiſhed any thing in Print, in the Pulpit he did. A man of ſo ordinary
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:109812:43"/> parts, that it was ſome time before he could paſs his examination to be made a Miniſter, after this he preached this new Doctrine, and was for it cenſured <hi>in the Star-chamber,</hi> and recanted it, and died obſcurely at <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</hi> But this is that which I deſire may be noted, he (ſay our Hiſtorians) <hi>equally preached up the obligation of the other Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal rites.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next was <hi>Theophilus Brabourn,</hi> ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally a <hi>Trader in Stockins,</hi> after made a Miniſter, and 1628. he publiſhed <hi>a book for the Jewiſh Sabbath,</hi> a book (to give it its due) wherein a thouſand times more is ſaid for it, and to anſwer arguments againſt his ſide, than in all Books ever wrote before or ſince. He hath been abundantly anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by divers (though on differing Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples) he lived till within theſe few years; till he came to aſſert <hi>three Gods,</hi> and grew to keep <hi>no Sabbath,</hi> for on his <hi>ſeventh day</hi> he would ordinarily make Bargains, take in intereſt Money, let out more, ſeal Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Mr. <hi>Ockford</hi> was another, what he was, where or how he lived, what he held more, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I cannot tell.</p>
               <p>The next was Mr. <hi>Tilham,</hi> who at <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi> in <hi>Eſſex</hi> made much ſtir about this
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:109812:43"/> point, and wrote one or two Books. He was reported before to have been a Papiſt, ſure I am his Books ſhew not the learning of an ordinary School-boy. With him one <hi>Pooly</hi> (a wild-headed <hi>Norfolk</hi> Preacher) joyned, he was a man of a raſh, giddy head, and Principles. Both theſe after went over Seas, where (I preſume our Brethren know upon too good information) they both were <hi>circumciſed,</hi> and to what elſe they ran I know not. I ſpeak not this (God knows) to upbraid, or mock at our Brethren, but by theſe examples, to ſhew them the tendency of this opinion, and practice, whither it leadeth poor Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. This <hi>Tilhams</hi> Book (though I think one of the weakeſt and abſurdeſt ever wrote on the ſubject) is what my Brethren in theſe parts glory in. I know for a Teacher, by a <hi>lively voice,</hi> they had a perſon of much more worth than <hi>Brahourn, Pooly,</hi> or <hi>Tilham,</hi> Mr. <hi>Rich. Breviter</hi> (who I perſwade my ſelf is at reſt with God) he was a good Scholler, and a perſon of a ſober life, and conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious to his Principles, and to whom the Name of Chriſt I think was truly precious; how far he had drank in this opinion, and to what degree he was perſwaded of it, I
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:109812:44"/> cannot tell. Sure I am, never ſo much as to print any diſcourſe for it. But I ſhall add no more upon this (I am ſure) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing ſubject.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If our brethren would avoid this charge, the next I am ſure they cannot. <hi>To obſerve the ſeventh day ſabbath, is to non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communion our ſelves from all Churches that ever were, or are in the world.</hi> I mean <hi>Goſpel-Churches.</hi> To ſay nothing of the time paſt, Chriſtian-Churches alwayes condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them as Hereticks, that kept that Sabbath (upon which account the <hi>Ebionites</hi> were condemned,) I do not think un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of our brethrens ſad thoughts. That this day there is no conſiderable number of Chriſtians under Heaven any where, that keep the Sabbath they keep. Our Brethren know that I am no great man for <hi>Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> But certainly the <hi>cuſtom</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> of the <hi>whole Church,</hi> in <hi>all times,</hi> and <hi>in all places,</hi> not contradicted by any valuable number of perſons of any perſwaſion, is not to be deſpiſed by any but ſuch as will ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate to themſelves, more knowledge of the mind of God than all the world beſides. I muſt confeſs, I doubt whether there be any one univerſal tradition except this; nor
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:109812:44"/> is this purely ſuch: but my meaning is, that there is no one thing as to which the practice of the whole Church in all ages is ſo on all ſides confeſſed, and out of doubt. Now the ſtrength of this lies here. <hi>It is not reaſonable to think that God ſhould leave his whole Church, in all times, to ſuch a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake as to the ſolemn time of worſhip.</hi> The general ſenſe of the faithful is upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count juſtly valuable in moſt controverted points. I ſpare inſtances here, they are abundantly given by Dr. <hi>Young,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Warren.</hi> Where the learned of our brethren may find them. I profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly write to my neighbours, who I know would be little edified by quotations in <hi>Greek and Latin.</hi> To leave therefore the practice of the former times, from the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Apoſtles times; which is very ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, at leaſt together with what evidence we have in the holy writ.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I ſay <hi>there is no preſent Churches of our brethrens mind or practice.</hi> So as <hi>they plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caſt off communion with all Churches of Chriſt on the Earth;</hi> and deprive their ſouls of the great advantage which they might have by it, and certainly this is no light thing to thoſe who know their Saviours
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:109812:45"/> walks <hi>in the mideſt of the golden candleſticks,</hi> (and ſurely they ſhould be near him, where he is.) To evidence this, I perceive many of them wholy abſenting themſelves from all religious meetings on the <hi>Lords day</hi> (the only ſolemn time obſerved by all Chriſtians near them) it may be in prudence and to avoid ſcandal they do not openly labour, but neither are they will that day worſhiping God. If any of them will that day go hear a Sermon, I appeal to them, whether they go as to a Sabbath duty, with that prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, with that faith in the promiſes to them who keep the Lords Sabbath as they ſhould go who expect a bleſſing from <hi>the Lord of the Sabbath.</hi> Ah! my brethren is it nothing to you? Is it nothing to you to have your places empty at the Lords ſolemn aſſemblies? to be out when the joint-fighs, prayers, and tears of Gods people, are pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out before the Lord? if indeed you could judge none fearing God but your ſelves, it were ſome plea: but I know you have more charity: why are you then di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided from them? why will you then loſe the advantage of their prayers? and deny them the advantage of your prayers? I muſt profeſs were there nothing elſe to keep
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:109812:45"/> me off, this very one thing would keep me off from that opinion. Eccl. 3.10. <hi>Woe to him that is alone, when he falleth: for he hath not another to help him up:</hi> Of the gifts and graces of how many precious mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and the advantage you might have from them, do you deprive your ſelves? Have your ſouls no need of their interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of Scriptures? their opening Goſpel myſteries, their powerful exhortations, and arguments for holineſs, their directions for your Chriſtian converſation? I beſeech you reflect upon your own ſouls, ſince the time that (in zeal to this opinion) you di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided your ſelves from the generality of Chriſtians. Have your ſouls proſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as formerly? Have you ſo increaſed in the knowledge of God? Have you had ſuch love, and zeal for God? have you ſo grown in any exerciſe of grace? Indeed it is not reaſonable for any to think that you ſhould, you have not had the means. This is not an age in which the Lord worketh in a way of miracles: but produceth his great works by means fitted to them. Our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren muſt be very partiall to themſelves, and their preſent teachers, if they think them, for <hi>gifts</hi> and <hi>graces,</hi> comparable to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:109812:46"/> thoſe godly, and able miniſters, under who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> miniſtry they formerly ſate. The Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſayes of Mr. <hi>Thrask,</hi> that beſides a <hi>voice,</hi> he had nothing: we know how little judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>Brabourn</hi> had in any thing, but <hi>this one point:</hi> And how little Mr. <hi>Tilham</hi> had, there needs no further witneſs then his own book, where is vanity and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs enough. Souls cannot feed upon a meer aiery, empty, roaring voice, it is the word of God they live upon, the word of God truly, judiciouſly, and faithfully opened, and powerfully applied. I appeal to our brethrens conſciences, whether they judge their preſent teachers, ſo able and fit for this work, as the Godly able miniſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Chriſt, who have wholly given up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the ſtudy of the Scriptures: and to the ſearch of the mind of God in them. I do not ſpeak for every one that hath the confidence to wear a gown. But I am ſure our brethren know and will acknowledg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, that all parts of <hi>England</hi> are filled with ſome number, or others of able faithful preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Now certainly it is no ſmall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage to our brethren, to deprive themſelves of all the gifts, and labours of theſe ſervants of God, while they
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:109812:46"/> walk alone erecting teachers to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> That for any to deprive themſelves of the liberty God hath indulged us to labour ſix dayes in each week, is not without guilt.</head>
               <p>IT is the Apoſtles Precept that <hi>we ſhould ſtand faſt in the liberty with which Chriſt hath made us free;</hi> and doubtleſs we are no more to deprive our ſelves of that liberty which our great Creator hath indulged us, than to throw away the life, health or eſtate with which he hath bleſſed us. It is one thing for us as our free-will offering to ſet apart one of the dayes which God hath given us for our own occaſions, for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God; another thing for us to think our ſelves obliged to do this, and to do it in a pretended Conſcience to a command, when we have no ſuch command. Since it hath pleaſed God to caſt my lot in the Countrey, I muſt profeſs I have moſt hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pitied ſome of my Brethren baptized in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this perſwaſion, to ſee them in the time
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:109812:47"/> of Harveſt, by their perſwaſion hindred of a third part of their time, from making uſe of thoſe ſeaſons which the gracious God hath indulged them for gathering in the fruits of the Earth. The ſeventh day of the week they reſt, (being perſwaded it is the Lords Sabbath) and the <hi>next day</hi> again, either out of conſcience to a command, or to avoid ſcandall, and danger of the Laws; and I have ſometimes thus ſaid with my ſelf: Alas for my Brethren! they are <hi>zealouſly affected</hi> (they would not elſe for a private opinion indanger the loſs of their Crops, which God hath given them) how good were this zeal <hi>if it were in a good cauſe?</hi> but hath God required ſuch things at their hands? hath not the Lord ſaid, <hi>Six dayes thou ſhalt labour, and do all thou haſt to do?</hi> Suppoſe theſe men by this devotion to loſe their crop, or a great part of it, or at leaſt to loſe much in it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> what ſatisfaction could they have other than from their own fancy? will it in the great day of account appear any ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er than a <hi>ſelf-robbery?</hi> for a <hi>Will-worſhip?</hi> either it will prove ſo, or the whole Chriſtian World is miſtaken, and hath been ſo from the very time Chriſt aſcended up into Heaven. Can my Brethren think,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:109812:47"/> That the Spirit that <hi>dwells</hi> in all Believers, and <hi>leadeth them into all truth,</hi> ſhould leave <hi>all the Churches of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>come and reveal himſelf</hi> in this <hi>ſingular notion</hi> unto them? Can our brethren think it is not poſſible that in this thing they ſhould be miſtaken? Surely they cannot think, but if whole Churches may err, and if they can think that all the Churches of God in this thing have for 1600 years been miſtaken, they <hi>may be miſtaken.</hi> Further yet, is it <hi>not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>robable, that our Brethren ſhould be miſtaken?</hi> Our Brethren muſt confeſs, that the far greater number of Chriſtians are of another mind, yea and not only of thoſe who are Chriſtians at large, baptized, and owning Chriſt as the Saviour of the World, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f thoſe who are <hi>Chriſtians indeed;</hi> I mean, who have not only imbraced the Doctrine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Faith, but in whom is the <hi>work of Faith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ith power, purifying their hearts,</hi> and who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>all their converſations exerciſe themſelves to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>p a good conſcience both towards God and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>owards men.</hi> Of theſe more than a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and for one are of a contrary mind to our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rethren in this point; ſo that I cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut think that our brethren, muſt needs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n mature thoughts conceive, that as it is
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:109812:48"/> poſſible they may be miſtaken, becauſe they are but men, ſo it is probable if not more than probable, that they are miſtaken, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the very far greater number of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who are as inquiſitive after the will of God as our Brethren are, as much afraid of ſinning againſt God, as our brethren, and as able to finde out the will of God as our brethren are, yet are of another mind, and that not only upon a <hi>tradition,</hi> or <hi>cuſtom,</hi> running along with a multitude at adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but upon a moſt ſerious debating, and arguing the buſineſs, and candid hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all that can be ſaid on the other ſide. I ſay, theſe things being conſidered, ſurely our brethren muſt judge it probable that they are miſtaken: It is not likely that their natural or acquired parts ſhould be more than thoſe of them who are againſt them; nay it is moſt certain they are ſhort of them: And what can our brethren have to incline them to think, that God hath left all his faithfull Miniſters, all his precious people, who ſtudy his will, and ſerve him, and beg his direction with prayers, and tears, night and day, and in ſo great a point as this left them to erre, and revealed himſelf only to theſe few of our brethren. Now if it be
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:109812:48"/> poſſible, that our brethren may be miſtaken, if it be probable that they are miſtaken, all our brethren can ſay is, <hi>That it is poſſible they may not be miſtaken, but that all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans (except themſelves) are in the error,</hi> and they are verily <hi>perſwaded that it is ſo.</hi> Truly conſidering the great numbers of the moſt learned, and ſtrictly godly perſons, who have all along been otherwiſe perſwaded, and for fifteen or ſixteen hundred years have been ſo, and lived in the contrary practice, it is hardly poſſible to imagine they ſhould, or that indeed they ſhould be miſtaken, becauſe they cannot be preſumed to have been without the preſence of Chriſt and the guidance of the infallible Spirit. If indeed what our Brethren ſometimes ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt, this practice were contrary to the fourth Commandement, if that had been ſo penned, as the ſenſe muſt neceſſarily be what they contend for, it had been ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. But when the Commandement is ſo penned, that unleſs they will be wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully partial to themſelves, they muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſs, that the fourth Commandement may remain an inviolable Law, and yet the <hi>ſame Sabbath</hi> may not be required by it to be obſerved by us, which at the giving of that
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:109812:49"/> Precept was in force amongſt the <hi>Jewes.</hi> Certainly our Brethren muſt labour under a great miſtake in this point, rather than all other Churches of Chriſt otherwiſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded. I muſt confeſs, it is our brethrens unhappineſs, that whiles they are thus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded it were ſin for them to act againſt the perſwaſion, or ſtrong opinion of their conſcience, yet in not acting contrary, they alſo ſin againſt God. This is the miſery un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which an erroneous Conſcience bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thoſe who are under the miſerable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of it; all therefore that I would do by this diſcourſe, is but to reform our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns underſtanding, and to offer ſuch things to them, as through Gods bleſſing may firſt bring them to another perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and then to another practice. That while they agree with us in the ſame ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fical acts of Worſhip, they may alſo agree with us in the ſame numericall acts, and in the ſame ſolemn time alſo. And certainly, I have ſaid enough, if our brethren bring no more prejudice to the reading of this diſcourſe, than I have had in the writing of it, to induce thoſe of our brethren who have any candor, to think that they are in a miſtake. Indeed the whole ſtreſs lies
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:109812:49"/> upon a right underſtanding of the <hi>Fourth Commandement;</hi> and I ſhall now leave it to our brethren ſeriouſly to adviſe, whether they can judge that, the neceſſary ſenſe of that Precept, which they muſt make ſo, or it will ſerve them in no ſtead. I deſigned at firſt but a very ſhort and plain Diſcourſe, I ſhall therefore here break it off, and make up the reſt in Prayers, both for us and our Brethren, that God would <hi>clear up all our doubts, correct all our miſtakes, pardon all our failings, make us all of one heart, and one way, and lead us into all truth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="exhortation">
            <pb facs="tcp:109812:50"/>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:109812:50"/>
            <head>An Exhortation to the more ſtrict obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Sabbath, where are Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, and motives to that great piece of our duty.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Had here laid aſide my pen, and have only taken it up again upon a ſuggeſtion, that ſome of our Brethren ſhould ſay unto me according to that Proverb, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.23. <hi>Phyſitian heal thy ſelf.</hi> Speak to thoſe of your own perſwaſion in this point, that they would keep their <hi>Sabbath,</hi> more like a <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi> than they do, and certainly it is far more excuſable, to keep any day of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with a religion befitting a Sabbath, than for any, while they declare againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> and thoſe who appear to them to <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daize</hi> in this point; to be indeed zealous for
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:109812:51"/> no <hi>Sabbath</hi> at all. And indeed, in this thing our brethren would have a great advantage againſt too many of us, if themſelves did not ſeverely obſerve their <hi>ſeventh day,</hi> but I obſerve too many of them as remiſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s others, ſo as while our zeal is ſpent about keeping <hi>ſeveral Sabbaths,</hi> neither party are ſo univerſally conſciencious as they ought to be in keeping any. This hath made me judge it worth the while to reſume my pen, and me-thinks I hear (as ſoon as I have done it) God ſpeaking to me as to <hi>Hoſea</hi> on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther argument. <hi>Plead with your Mother</hi> (and with your brethren) <hi>plead,</hi> for <hi>ſhe is not my wife, neither am I her husband, Let her therefore put away</hi> her Sabbath neglects <hi>out of my ſight,</hi> and her Sabbath profanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from her: <hi>Leſt I ſtrip her naked as in the day wherein ſhe was born: and make her as a wilderneſs, and ſet her like a dry land, and ſlay her with thirſt: Hoſea</hi> 2.2, 3. And indeed what <hi>Luther</hi> (with reſpect to <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> in matter of <hi>Doctrine</hi>) was wont to ſay of the <hi>Doctrine, and Article of Juſtification:</hi> the ſame I think may be ſaid, as to <hi>obſervation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Sabbath,</hi> with reference to <hi>holineſs</hi> in a <hi>Church, and its members.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is <hi>Articulus ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; cade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>is Eccleſſae,</hi>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:109812:51"/> The Article of a ſtanding, or declining Church: It will upon obſervation be found true, that the ſtrictneſs and holyneſs of <hi>Life</hi> found either in ſocieties of people, or in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons, will be in degree much ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their zeal or remiſneſs in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Sabbath.</p>
            <p>In what things the <hi>ſanctification of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi> lieth, we ſhall beſt learn from the Scripture, and we can be no other way in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. For though the light of nature ſhewing us a God, the law of nature oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us to worſhip him, and by conſequence to ſet ſome time apart for it (for all humane actions muſt be done in time) yet nature di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth us not to <hi>a ſeventh,</hi> nor to <hi>this ſeventh,</hi> nor yet to thoſe <hi>acts</hi> of <hi>worſhip,</hi> which God requireth of us.</p>
            <p>We are (I ſuppoſe) agreed that both the old and new Teſtament ought to be eyed as our rule in the caſe, and indeed the old teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is moſt full in its directions of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. In the new we find the <hi>Sabbath alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> the <hi>Jewiſh ſuperſtitions</hi> and miſ-interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations corrected, the practical obſervation of it juſtified, by the Examples of our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and others; but the rules about it are but few. Our Lord intending
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:109812:52"/> to leave his people (as in many other points of the moral Law,) to the fuller directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>the Laws</hi> and <hi>the Prophets.</hi> Now in the old Teſtament, we find ſomthing in the Law: (in the five books of <hi>Moſes</hi>) ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the Prophets.</p>
            <p>The Original Law we find <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. (for concerning the Sabbath in the Patriarchs time, I ſhall ſay nothing, it being not my queſtion to examine when the obſervation began, but how it ſhould be obſerved.)</p>
            <p>The fourth commandment, plainly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth that it ſhould be kept <hi>as on holy reſt,</hi> it requires it to be kept as a day of reſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and requireth us to keep it <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> ſo <hi>Exod.</hi> 35.2. an <hi>holy day,</hi> a <hi>Sabbath of reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſt</hi> is oppoſed to <hi>Motion,</hi> and <hi>Action.</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs is oppoſed to <hi>idleneſs,</hi> and <hi>filthineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay firſt Reſt is oppoſed to
<list>
                  <item>Motion</item>
                  <item>Action</item>
               </list> yet it is apparent from ſcripture that neither all <hi>Motion,</hi> nor all <hi>action</hi> fall under the <hi>prohibition of that precept.</hi> We ſhall find both our Saviour and his Apoſtles going into the Synagogues on the <hi>Sabbath day:</hi> and the latter going out of the City. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.13. hence <hi>Act.</hi> 1.13. we read of a <hi>Sabbath dayes journey. i. e.</hi> ſuch
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:109812:52"/> a journey as a man might lawfully take on the Sabbath day: what length that might be hath (poſſibly unneceſſarily) troubled ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, doubtleſs ſo much is to be underſtood as one might conveniently go to attend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the worſhip of God, it is no improbable conjecture, <hi>That the phraſe hath reference to the firſt ſettlement of the Jewiſh Church upon their march in the wilderneſs.</hi> There were to be 200 hundred Cubits between the <hi>Arke</hi> and the <hi>Camp, Joſh.</hi> 3.4. And in probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity when they reſted, they were to keep the ſame diſtance; (this ſome interpret one mile, others two miles.) On the Sabbath day, they all were to come up to the <hi>Ark</hi> to worſhip, which was 200 hundred Cubits diſtant from the neareſt of them: and at a far greater diſtance from thoſe who incamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed fartheſt off the Ark. <hi>Godwin</hi>'s <hi>Jewiſh Antiquities l.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. Beſides this, we ſhall eaſily underſtand what Motion is lawful on the Sabbath day, if we underſtand what <hi>Action</hi> is lawful: For ſuch <hi>Motion</hi> as is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſuch Action, muſt alſo be lawful. So it is lawful for a Phyſitian to go to his patient. For a man having a beaſt fallen into a pit, to go to help it out, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, as all <hi>Motion</hi> from our places is
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:109812:53"/> not prohibited, ſo neither in all action: Our <hi>Actions</hi> are divided into ſuch as are <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> flowing from a principle, and neceſſity of nature, and ſerving to the upholding and conſervation of nature, As eating, drinking, ſleeping, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Under the notion of <hi>moral actions</hi> we comprehend, all our actions of worldly labour in our callings and places. By <hi>religious actions</hi> we underſtand <hi>acts of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> by which we give an homage to God. The fourth commandment requires that we ſhould <hi>do no manner of work:</hi> but it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from other Scriptures, that all actions, all work is forbidden. To open to you the mind of God in this thing a little.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Acts of Religious worſhip, or tending di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to it, are ſo far from being forbidden that they are commanded.</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> might kill, and offer beaſts for ſacrifices, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 23.31. <hi>Num.</hi> 28.9, 10. The Prieſts might order the lamps, ſet on the <hi>new bread,</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> might <hi>circumciſe an infant.</hi> The <hi>Scribes</hi> might <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the Law.</hi> They might blow their <hi>trumpets</hi> to call the aſſembly, <hi>Num.</hi> 10.2, 10. <hi>Watch</hi> to prevent the profanation of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, <hi>&amp;c. Neh.</hi> 13.22. Whence the <hi>Jews</hi> were wont to ſay that <hi>In the temple</hi> there was <hi>no Sabbath,</hi> no reſt there, all were
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:109812:53"/> at work. In analogy to this there can be no doubt, but it is lawful to <hi>ſtudy, preach, read, hear, pray, ſing, baptize</hi> on the Lords day, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereto, to ring Bells, to call people toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; to be imployed in ſeeing to others ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of it. Theſe ſort of actions is ſo far from being unlawful, that they are acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the Sabbath. <hi>Opus diei in die ſuo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond ſort of action lawful on the Sabbath day, are ſuch as are <hi>neceſſary to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the being or well-being of creatures.</hi> Thus it is lawful for Phyſitians, or Chirurgions to apply medicines to their patients. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour abundantly vindicates this, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5, 9. <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.12, 13. <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.10. And ſo for nurſes to attend thoſe that are ſick, or young children, to go for a Phyſitian; to prepare phyſick, let blood, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To ſave the life of another, to indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our to preſerve our own lives, by fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in oppoſition to an enemy, by fleeing from an enemy, to be in arms for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of our Prince, or Country, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 20.9. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.5, 6. For the Magiſtrate to commit <hi>malefactors, Numb.</hi> 15.34. To <hi>dreſs meat,</hi> (our Saviour juſtified the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples rubbing ears of Corn, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12, 1, 2, 3.) We find our Saviour at a feaſt on the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:109812:54"/> Sabbath day, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.1, 2, 3. and others were bidden, <hi>v.</hi> 7. To <hi>feed</hi> and <hi>water</hi> cattle juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by our Saviour, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.15. To keep our goods from being loſt, upon which our Saviour <hi>Job.</hi> 5. juſtified the <hi>lame man carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his bed.</hi> Undoubtedly actions that tend to preſerve the being or uſefulneſs of a thing, of which we have a moral certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that without ſuch labour on the Sabbath, the creature would periſh, or be unuſeful, and corrupt, are lawful on the Lords day. This all ſtands upon that principle: That <hi>God loves mercy rather than ſacrifice.</hi> And up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that principle,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Actions alſo of <hi>mercy</hi> and <hi>charity,</hi> are by all Determined lawful. Such as are <hi>viſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſick, &amp;c.</hi> Many of thoſe which come under the Schoolemens two verſes,
<q>Viſito, poto, cibo, redimo, tego, colligo, condo.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Giving <hi>bread to the hungry, beer to the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, burying</hi> the <hi>dead,</hi> relieving the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So as we find the reſt commanded in the fourth commandment limited by theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, and it muſt remain unlawful in any
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:109812:54"/> other cauſes to labour. From whence we may gather,</p>
            <p>That the prohibitions we read of in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of not <hi>kindling a fire on the Sabbath day, Exod.</hi> 35. and <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.29. <hi>For not going out of their place on the ſeventh day, to gather manna:</hi> muſt not be taken in that ſtrictneſs, in which ſome would urge them, or at leaſt only concerned the <hi>Jews</hi> in that time, not afterward. The <hi>fire forbidden</hi> to be kindled, muſt neceſſarily be underſtood, 1. <hi>Either in reference to the making the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle,</hi> of which he there ſpeaks; or 2. more largely of any <hi>trade-fire</hi> kindled for men to work with, to get a livelihood, not ſuch as is kindled for <hi>dreſſing of meat, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing us in cold weather;</hi> or when we are <hi>ſick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. It is not probable there was no fire in the <hi>Jews</hi> houſes that made the feaſt, at which our Saviour was, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14. beſides we find works paralell to this, juſtified in Scripture. <hi>Though going out of their doors on the Sabbath,</hi> muſt be underſtood, to <hi>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manna, Exod.</hi> 16.29. or upon other ends, than in order to actions of <hi>piety, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſity,</hi> or preſervation and mercy, for that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſtance, <hi>Numh.</hi> 15.32, 33. The Scripture
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:109812:55"/> ſo ſhortly relates that ſtory of the mans being put to death for gathering ſticks on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day, as to the cauſe of it, that it is hard to give a ſatisfactory anſwer. <hi>Stoning to death</hi> was a puniſhment uſed in the higheſt caſes, as that of blaſphemy, &amp;c. with which our reaſon would not judge ſuch a violation of the Sabbath, as gathering ſticks was to be put in the ballance: but in the Judgement there could be no error, for it was given by the Judge of the whole Earth, who cannot err in appointing puniſhments to ſins: That he <hi>gathered ſticks on the Sabbath,</hi> and this was the matter of his guilt, is plain, but whether it was after ſome <hi>ſpecial command of Moſes</hi> to the contrary (which the ſcripture ſaith not) or to aſſert a profane liberty, and his not regarding the commandment of God, when he had no need to it: Or whether it was in order to kindle ſome fire for labour contrary to the precept, <hi>Exod.</hi> 35.3. Or what other circumſtance fell in to aggravate the action to ſuch a degree of guilt we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell. Suppoſe it was to kindle a neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fire, yet we are ſure it might have been done before the <hi>Sabbath;</hi> ſo as it was an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary labour, as to any neceſſity but what a former neglect had created: ſomething
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:109812:55"/> was doubtleſs in it more than we have in the ſtory. It is certain <hi>Moſes</hi> brings this exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple next after the Law againſt preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſinners, <hi>Num.</hi> 15.30, 31, 32. Nor do we read afterwards of any ſuch examples of ſev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rity.</p>
            <p>But enough is ſaid to ſhew how the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath ſhould be kept as a reſt from labour.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But this is not all, it is called an <hi>holy reſt, the reſt of the holy Sabbath,</hi> and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment expreſly ſaith, <hi>Remember to keep it holy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now an holy reſt certainly ſtands diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from a reſt <hi>meerly natural,</hi> when our bodies ceaſe from action, and worldly labour, 2. A <hi>reſt</hi> that is <hi>profane.</hi> By which I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not only a <hi>ſinful reſt,</hi> unlawful on any day; but a reſt from <hi>recreations,</hi> and <hi>paſtimes,</hi> lawful enough on other dayes. We read not in the old Law of any toleration for ſports on the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> we read on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary that it was to be <hi>an holy reſt, kept holy,</hi> &amp;c. To which ſports cannot contribute: It ſeems unreaſonable to think that labour ſhould be forbidden, in order to our more ſerious and ſolemn ſervice of God, and yet ſports ſhould be allowed, which every way as much diſtract, and unfit the Soul for acts
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:109812:56"/> of ſolemn worſhip. But the prophets are beſt interpreters of the Law. Now the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah, Iſa.</hi> 58.13. expounding this Law ſaith, <hi>If thou turn away thy foot from the Sabbath, from doing thy pleaſure on my holy-day, and call the Sabbath a delight, the holy of the Lord, honourable, and ſhalt honour him, not doing thine own wayes, nor finding thy own pleaſure, nor ſpeaking thy own words: Then ſhalt thou delight thy ſelf in the Lord, and I will cauſe thee to ride upon the high places of the Earth, and feed thee with the heritage of</hi> Jacob <hi>thy father, for the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it.</hi> There is a <hi>precept v.</hi> 13. and a <hi>promiſe</hi> annexed to the due obſervance of that precept <hi>v.</hi> 14. The precept is directive for the ſanctification of the Sabbath, which is called <hi>the Sabbath, the Lords holy day.</hi> The end of the Sabbath for which God inſtituted it, and which every one ought in the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it to aim at; <hi>and ſhalt honour him,</hi> the honouring and glorifying of God, that is the end. Then you have the manner directed, how you ſhould honour God in it,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By a reverent eſteem of it, calling it <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable.</hi> 2. By a free and chearful entertaining it, <hi>calling it a delight.</hi> 3. By an abſtaining
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:109812:56"/> from <hi>our own pleaſure,</hi> our own <hi>words,</hi> our <hi>own wayes,</hi> and <hi>turning our foot from it.</hi> Our own <hi>pleaſure, word, wayes</hi> certainly ſignify ſuch pleaſure, ſuch words, ſuch wayes as we meerly ſerve and gratifie our ſelves by, and bring no immediate honour and glory to God. Now whether this be not as excluſive of all <hi>recreations, ſports, paſtimes,</hi> &amp;c. as of all laborious actions (other than thoſe before excepted by warrant from the word of God,) I leave to every conſcientious and ſober Chriſtian to conſider with himſelf and judge.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only further add, that what Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines truly ſay of all other moral precepts, muſt be true of this. That where an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is in any precept forbidden, all words and thoughts relating to it are alſo forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and this is alſo hinted by the prophet in ſpecial, in thoſe words <hi>not ſpeaking thy own words.</hi> I am not ignorant that many of our brethren in the other reformed Churches are not of our minds in this point of the Sabbath. But,</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is therefore to be obſerved that they do not think the <hi>Sabbath moral,</hi> we do, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rge it as commanded us in the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:109812:57"/>2. And ſecondly upon inquiry we may poſſibly find, that both amongſt their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and People, thoſe who are moſt ſtrict in their lives, lament the looſeneſs of others of their Brethren in this thing, and order their perſonal demeanours, and their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies after another rate. However, we are to live by rule, and not by example. I have thus as ſhortly as I could opened your duty, and ſhewed you how the Sabbath is to be kept as a <hi>reſt,</hi> as an <hi>holy reſt unto the Lord.</hi> Let me now plead with my brethren, that knowing our Maſters will we may do it. I will urge a few arguments in the caſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>It is a piece of Religion, by which the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God have formerly more honoured God in theſe Nations, than in moſt, if not than in any other places.</hi> Profeſſors ſtrict obſervation of the Sabbath in <hi>England</hi> hath even from the beginning of the Reformation been <hi>their Crown</hi> and <hi>their Glory.</hi> Oh let not this Crown (in our dayes) fall from our heads. God hath alwayes had in this Nation a ſtrict Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath-obſerving people in the worſt of times: There have been of late greater light, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er means, more preaching, more Profeſſion than in former times; oh let there not be a leſs ſtrict Sabbath-keeping than formerly:
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:109812:57"/> This would be but an ill requitall of the God of their mercies. Men in other little things have a zeal to keep up the credit and repute of their Countrey, certainly it ſhould not in this grow cold. None certainly can think this is rather an argument on the other ſide, as intimating that my plea is for an unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary ſtrictneſs. If the opinion of duty in ſuch ſevere obſervation of Sabbaths, ſhould be a miſtake, yet unqueſtionably in the practice there can be no conſiderable miſtake on this hand: If a man upon any other day of the week, in order to the putting his heart into, and keeping his heart in the better frame for Religious Worſhip, to be in that day performed, ſhould reſolve to meddle with no labour, to allow himſelf no diverſions by <hi>Sports,</hi> nor to ingage in any worldly or more idle diſcourſe; certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly every one would ſay he did well, and can any be condemned either by another or by his own Conſcience, for doing this on the Sabbath-day, when by the confeſſion of all, they are obliged either by the fourth Commandment (as we ſay) or by the cuſtom or command of the Church (as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſay) to more, and more ſolemn acts of Worſhip, than upon the week-dayes?
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:109812:58"/> Surely, if we had not particular Precepts in the cauſe, yet the conſideration of the great and ſolemn ſervices we are that day to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to God, which reaſon will tell us, ſhould be performed with the beſt attention of minde, and intention of ſpirit, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved when done to the beſt advantage, would oblige us to this reſt from worldly actions, worldly diſcourſes, vain and uſeleſs pleaſures, which muſt neceſſarily divert our minds from our ſpiritual employments, and take up that time which might be better improved, in the concocting the Word we have heard, and due digeſting of it by me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, and applying it to our hearts. Now conſidering (over and above this) that this hath been the honour of the Profeſſours of Religion in <hi>England,</hi> it certainly ought to prevail with ingenuous children of ſo good Parents, eſpecially when it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that they ſhould find any errour in the practice, if any will fancy, that there is a miſtake as to the opinion of a neceſſity of ſuch ſtrictneſs. If any of them can ſay, (which I much doubt, yea I firmly believe the contrary) he that reads and prayes in his family, and prayes with the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and hears a Sermon or two in the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:109812:58"/> Sabbath, though he alſo in the vacation of theſe exerciſes, doth ſome worldly buſineſs and diſcourſeth of it, or recreates himſelf with ſome ſports (not ſinfull) <hi>doth well:</hi> yet they muſt ſay, he who forbears theſe <hi>ſports, labours, diſcourſes</hi> on that day, <hi>doth better,</hi> if not with reſpect to the command ſtrictly, yet with reference to the dutyes he is to perform, that he may the better perform them, and make the better im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement and advantage of them, and with reference to ſcandall, and the deſtroying the Souls of others, yea and in reference to his own Soul. Reaſon obliging us in ſuch caſes of doubt to take the ſafeſt part.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, Conſider, <hi>I beſeech you the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence that it hath upon an holy life, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation.</hi> Compare the lives of thoſe that are ſtrict in the obſervation of the Sabbath with the lives of thoſe that are more remiſs in it, and where you ſee an abatement as to ſtrictneſs in keeping Sabbaths, whether you do not find alſo a proportionable abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of holineſs almoſt in all their other converſe. Obſerve and ſee if they be as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious (according to <hi>Davids</hi> reſolution, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.2.) to <hi>walk in their houſe in a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect way.</hi> To <hi>inſtruct their Families</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:109812:59"/> to <hi>Abrahams</hi> copy, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding them to keep the way of the Lord.</hi> Teaching the Law of God unto <hi>their children diligently</hi> (and whetting it upon them as it is in the Hebrew) and <hi>talking of it when they ſit in their houſes, and when they walk in the way, when they lye down, and when they riſe up according to Gods command,</hi> Deut. 6.7. whether they be ſo diligent and conſtant in praying with their families, ſo offering up their morning and evening ſacrifices to the Lord. Indeed it is not reaſonable to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, that thoſe who will not ſpend the Sabbath thus, ſhould ſpend any conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble time of their working-dayes thus, when they have a free liberty to work by the Laws of God and men: conſidering eſpecially that on the Sabbath-day they are reſtrained from labour, not only by the Law of God, but by the Laws of the Nation, and general uſage and cuſtom of the place where they are. But I fear upon obſervation we ſhall finde, that thoſe who are looſe in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Sabbath, are not very ſtrict in any other piece of their converſation. I remember the learned <hi>Junius</hi> in his <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytick</hi> Explication of <hi>Numbers,</hi> upon the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry before mentioned concerning him that
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:109812:59"/> gathered ſticks, ſtarts a queſtion, whether then it was ſuch a crime to gather ſticks on the Sabbath day. He anſwers it thus, That the Precept of the Sabbath was the <hi>clauſula,</hi> the concluſion of all the Precepts that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned the Worſhip of God, in which God would have all exerciſes of piety imbibed, whence it was, that he who was in the leaſt guilty of the profanation of that, was guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a profanation of the whole Worſhip of God. Again, that Chriſtian who is poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with a <hi>dread of the Lord</hi> as to the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, and walks in that dread all that day, will find it influential upon him the whole week, ſo that the ſtrict obſervation of the Sabbath is both influential upon us as to holineſs, and is alſo an indication of holineſs, which ſhould oblige Chriſtians to the ſtrict obſervation of it. <hi>Buxtorf</hi> tells us of one of the Jewiſh <hi>Rabbies,</hi> that wiſhed <hi>His por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion might be with thoſe that began the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath with thoſe of</hi> Tiberias, <hi>and ended it with thoſe of</hi> Tſeppore. That is, who ſanctified the Sabbath in the longeſt proportion of time: for <hi>Tſephore</hi> being a City placed on the top of a Mountain, the Sun ſhined longer upon that than upon others, and <hi>Tiberias</hi> being ſituated in a valley, the Sun appeared
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:109812:60"/> to them not ſo ſoon as to others. I think it may be a good wiſh for a Chriſtian, <hi>That his portion might be with them, that begin the Sabbath ſooneſt, and end it lateſt, and keep it moſt ſtrictly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Methinks the typical notion of the Sabbath ſhould ſomething oblige us.</hi> The Sabbath is not only a conſequent, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorative ſign to us of Chriſts reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but it is alſo a predictional, and antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſign of that glorious <hi>reſt</hi> which remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for the people of God; which way ſoever we look upon it, it certainly calleth to us, for a ſtrict obſervation of it. 1. <hi>Let us look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it</hi> as a <hi>conſequent ſign,</hi> as a <hi>memorial of the reſurrection of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> We are ſaid to be <hi>riſen with Chriſt,</hi> whence the Apoſtle argues our duty, to <hi>ſeek thoſe things which are above. To ſet our affections on things above.</hi> Certainly, as our intereſt in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Chriſt, and the influence it hath upon us ſhould ingage us to ſeek the things above, in the whole courſe of our lives, and at all times to ſet our affections upon things above; ſo not to do it upon that day which God hath ſanctified for our ſpecial com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration of it, will ſpeak ſouls both lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſenſible of the great mercy of redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:109812:60"/> and little influenced from that reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, not <hi>riſen with Chriſt</hi> as we ought to be. Again, let us conſider the Chriſtian Sabbath, as a ſign <hi>antecedent,</hi> and prefigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative. The Apoſtle ſeemeth thus to argue, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.8, 9. <hi>There remains therefore a reſt to the people of God. For he who is entred into his reſt, he alſo hath ceaſed from his own work as God did from his. Let us labour therefore to enter into that reſt.</hi> And a little before, <hi>v.</hi> 4, 5, 6, 7. of the ſame Chapter. <hi>For he ſpake in a certain place of the ſeventh day on this wiſe, And God did reſt the ſeventh day from all his works, And in this place again, if they ſhall enter into my reſt. Seeing therefore it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth, that ſome muſt enter therein, and they to whom it was firſt preached entered not in becauſe of unbelief. Again he limiteth a certain day in</hi> David, <hi>ſaying, To day, after ſo long a time as it is ſaid, To day if you will hear his voice harden not your hearts: for if Jeſus had given them reſt, he would not have ſpoken of another day. There remains therefore,</hi> &amp;c. The Apoſtles great buſineſs there (as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent) is to exhort the believing <hi>Hebrews</hi> to a <hi>perſeverance in the profeſſion of the Goſpel,</hi> and to perſwade thoſe that yet believed not, to imbrace it. The argument which he
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:109812:61"/> uſeth, is, Leſt they ſhould fail of an entrance into Gods reſt; by which reſt he undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly means the ſouls reſt in Heaven. To this end he tells them,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That there is ſuch a reſt,</hi> v. 9.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That there is a Promiſe left of entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That ſome, and thoſe to whom it wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> firſt preached, entred not in becauſe of unbelief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That there is a day limited in which thoſe muſt hear the Lords voice, that will enter into this reſt.</hi> That there is ſuch a <hi>Reſt,</hi> he proveth by two types. The one that of <hi>Canaan,</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> after their laborious tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing in the Wilderneſs entring into <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> v. 3. The ſecond is that of the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> for what ſenſe elſe can thoſe words have in this place? <hi>He ſpoke in a certain place, of the ſeventh day on this wiſe, And God did reſt the ſeventh day from all his work.</hi> And <hi>v.</hi> 10. of Chriſt he ſaith, <hi>he that is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into his reſt, he alſo ceaſed from his own works as God did from his.</hi> God the Fathers proper work was <hi>Creation,</hi> the <hi>Sons</hi> proper work, was <hi>Redemption.</hi> When God had fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed his work, he <hi>reſted,</hi> and in comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration of it, he appointed his people to keep a <hi>day of Reſt:</hi> When Chriſt had finiſhed
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:109812:61"/> his work of <hi>redemption,</hi> he alſo <hi>reſted,</hi> and appointed us a day to <hi>reſt</hi> in, in commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of it; both the one and the other are by the Apoſtle made <hi>prefigurative</hi> of that <hi>Reſt</hi> which God hath prepared in Heaven for us; which alſo it ſelf is called, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a keeping of a Sabbath. Now certainly, the type ſhould bear a proportion to what is ſignified by it. Our reſt on Earth ſhould bear ſome proportion to our <hi>reſt in Heaven.</hi> Our reſt in Heaven ſhall not only be a <hi>ceſſation from labour,</hi> but from all <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual vain pleaſure,</hi> from all <hi>worldly diſcourſe,</hi> a continual pleaſure in beholding and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying God. If we would keep a Sabbath perfectly, certainly, (abating what is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for our ſelves or others, for the ſuſtentation of our bodyes, and the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation both of our ſelves and other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) we ſhould allow our ſelves no more labour than we ſhall have in Heaven, no other pleaſure than the Angels and Saints of God have there, all whoſe pleaſure is in the contemplation and injoyment of God. Oh that we could thus ſanctifie Sabbaths! But this is my third argument to preſs my Brethren to a more ſtrict obſervation of the Lords holy Day.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:109812:62"/>4. A fourth argument by which I ſhall pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this ſtrict ſanctification of the Sabbath, ſhall be <hi>the influence which it muſt neceſſarily hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon us, as to the duties of worſhip, which we perform on that day.</hi> There is hardly any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (unleſs thoſe given up to riot and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs) but hath upon him ſome little awe, and dread of the Sabbath: Some duties they think ſhould be done in it, more than upon another day, either out of <hi>Obedience</hi> to God (in the fourth commandment) or to the <hi>Church,</hi> or to the <hi>ſtate</hi> ſo commanding. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſome will ſhuffle off with very little. Some think hearing one is enough for their <hi>conſciences:</hi> In the afternoon they may la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, or ſport, &amp;c. Others think it is no matter whether there be a Sermon or no, but they think they ſhould be longer at <hi>morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and evening prayer</hi> that day than upon other dayes. Thoſe who have any degree of ſobriety in them judge that the greater part of the day ſhould be ſpent in the publick, or private exerciſe of Gods worſhip: but we are not ſo ſtrictly tied up, as to abſtinence from pleaſure, worldly labour, vain or ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar diſcourſe. I will for the preſent give them, what I cannot grant them, <hi>viz.</hi> that the precept is not ſo ſtrictly to be expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:109812:62"/> yet me thinks reaſon is enough in the caſe to enforce what we plead for. It may be (Chriſtian) thou art one of the latter ſort, a ſober p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſon, who doeſt think that the greateſt <hi>part of that day</hi> ſhould be ſpent in the <hi>ſolemn ſtated acts of worſhip,</hi> but think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt the <hi>intermediate time</hi> may be more looſly ſpent. Do but conſider, what an influence thy ſtrict, or looſer ſpending of the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate time muſt neceſſarily have upon thee.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>In reference to thy acts of worſhip.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>In reference to the effect and fruit of that worſhip.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, (I ſay) in reference to <hi>thy acts of worſhip.</hi> If thou haſt any thing of the ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of a Chriſtian in thee, thou wilt and muſt acknowledge, that God muſt be ſerved with thy ſpirit, and with the utmoſt ferven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of thy ſpirit without diſtractions, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any coldneſs and deadneſs of ſpirit, with life, love, delight in thy approach to God, &amp;c. Doſt thou think that all thy time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy acts of worſhip had not need be ſpent in <hi>reading,</hi> in <hi>holy meditations,</hi> in <hi>read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the word,</hi> &amp;c. That when thou comeſt to ſerve the Lord in ſolemn acts of worſhip, thy thoughts may not be ſcattered, thy heart
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:109812:63"/> may not be <hi>dull,</hi> and <hi>dead:</hi> certainly a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious Chriſtian finds all his time too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, before he falls upon his duty, to get his heart into ſuch a frame, and as he ſpends his previous, or intermediate time, leſs or more ſpiritually, ſo he will find his heart leſs or more what it ſhould be in the performance of his more direct, and ſolemn worſhip.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As to the <hi>effect or fruit of worſhip,</hi> that is, the impreſſion of it, which it leaves or the ſoul (for I ſhall here ſpeak nothing as to our pleaſing God by the acts of homage which we perform, which is the effect of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in reference to God.) We are commanded to <hi>deſire the ſincere milk of the word, that we may grow thereby,</hi> and certainly there is no ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Chriſtian, that goes out to hear a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, but doth propound to himſelf the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the knowledge of God, the increaſe of faith in God, the increaſe of the fear o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, the increaſe of love to God, and other graces. None goes to a Sacrament, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds to himſelf for his end, the meeting of God in the Ordinance, and receiving ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bleſſing from him, either as to ſpiritual <hi>life comfort,</hi> or <hi>ſtrength.</hi> Now I appeal to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reaſon of Chriſtians, whether in order <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this end, they had not need ſpend all the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:109812:63"/> Sabbath time, after the performance of their ſolemn acts of worſhip, meditating of what they have heard in the word, what they have <hi>ſeen,</hi> and <hi>heard,</hi> and <hi>done</hi> in a Sacrament; you know the parable of the ſower. The thorns (which our Saviour expounds, the <hi>cares of the world) choaked the word.</hi> The <hi>fowls of the air</hi> pickt up the ſeed, which fell by the way ſide: worldly thoughts, worldly diſcourſes, worldly buſineſs immediately after <hi>hearing,</hi> immediately after a Sacrament, are like thorns choaking the word, or Birds of the air picking up the ſeed. So as if we had no other argument than this, yet it were in this caſe not inconſiderable. But,</p>
            <p>Fifthly, methinks it ſhould ſomething pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with us to conſider <hi>how much ſtreſs God laies upon it.</hi> How many times doth he <hi>incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the precept?</hi> with how many additional precepts doth he hedge it? how ſeverely doth he puniſh the violators? how often is it mentioned as the very <hi>head of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> yea as the whole of it? I ſay firſt how often doth God inculcate it, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.23. (which text argueth it given before the law promulged in <hi>Sinai.) Exod.</hi> 20. <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.14. <hi>Lev.</hi> 23.3. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.3. and in abundance of other texts. With how
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:109812:64"/> many additional precepts did God hedge it? which (though ſome of them but tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary) yet argued Gods eye on the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Sabbath, ſuch as thoſe, <hi>for not ſtirring out of doors to gather Manna.</hi> Not kindling the artificers fire. How ſharply did God himſelf order the puniſhment of that poor wretch that gathered ſticks on that day? in purſuance of which the writers of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> antiquities tell us, <hi>Sabbath-breakers</hi> were wont to be ſtoned to death, as <hi>Idolaters, Blaſphemers, falſe Prophets,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>inceſtuous Perſons, Sodomites, Buggerers, burners of their children in ſacrifice to Molech. Witches, curſers of Parents, and ſuch as were rebelious againſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</hi> We read of none elſe ſtoned to death. (For I count <hi>inticers to idolatry, acceſſaries</hi> to theſe, under their principals.) The righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God appointed the ſame puniſhment to the <hi>Sabbath-breaker</hi> as to the vileſt and worſt of men: which letteth us ſee, what magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude this ſin of the violation of the Sabbath hath in the Lords eye. And if we look con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderately, we ſhall find, that the <hi>ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Sabbath,</hi> is by God looked upon as a duty of the firſt and higheſt ſort. It is made one of his moral and perpetual pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, it is uſhered in with a word of <hi>remark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:109812:64"/> Remember to keep holy the Sabbath day:</hi> The obſervation of it in the Precept is more particularly directed, <hi>Thou ſhalt do no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of work, thou, nor thy Son, nor thy Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nor thy man-ſervant, nor thy maid-ſervant, nor the Cattle within thy Gates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is joyned with the moſt <hi>natural,</hi> neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and momentous duties. <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.3. <hi>Fear every man his Father, and keep my Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths.</hi> It is mentioned in Scripture as the <hi>head of all Religion;</hi> and therefore choſen out by God, to expreſs all Religion by: and where the violation of all Religion is taxed, it is ordinarily taxed under this notion of not <hi>keeping, or profaning</hi> the <hi>Lords Sabbath,</hi> Ezek. 20.13, 16, 21, 24. <hi>ch.</hi> 23.38. and ſuppoſing the Promiſes made to the ſtrict obſervation of the <hi>Sabbath</hi> to be <hi>Synechdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall,</hi> and to be underſtood of ſuch as keep cloſe to, and are ſtrict in all pieces of <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Worſhip;</hi> yet Gods chooſing of this part of Worſhip to expreſs the whole by it, is ſufficient to let us know how much God ever laid upon the ſtrict obſervation of the Sabbath, as much as if God had told us, that without it we do nothing in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. It is worth the obſerving how croſs men are to God in this thing, tything <hi>mine
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:109812:65"/> and annis, and cummin, and making</hi> light of this far more <hi>weighty thing.</hi> We read in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed under the Jewiſh <hi>Poedagogy,</hi> of <hi>muſick</hi> and <hi>ſinging,</hi> and <hi>garments,</hi> uſed in the <hi>world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sanctuary</hi> (as the Apoſtle calls it) but we no where read of any Promiſes made to theſe more external rites, and little obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of bowing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we ſee many men zealous for theſe things, but oh how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in this great thing! not only violating the Precept, but of ſo debaucht conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as to <hi>teach men ſo to do,</hi> (which ſaith our Saviour is to <hi>make men leaſt in the Kingdom of God,</hi> Math. 5.) But certainly Chriſtians, we ſhould look as God doth, and lay the ſtreſs of our practice where he layes it. The Precept of the fourth Commandment is one thing, the Argument is another; who ſo ſaith the Precept, or any thing in that is ceremonial, leaves us but nine Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, contrary to the <hi>faith</hi> of all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God from the very beginning of the world; and they who will argue the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept temporary, becauſe the argument had but a temporary obligation, make a fair way to blot out the firſt Commandment, becauſe the Argument in the letter of it, only concerned the <hi>Jews,</hi> who were the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:109812:65"/> only people <hi>God brought out of the land of Egypt, out of the houſe of bondage:</hi> I ſay in the letter of it. I know we are alſo by Chriſt brought out of a <hi>ſpiritual Egypt,</hi> out of a <hi>ſpiritual bondage;</hi> and if we can thus blot out the firſt Commandment, and the fourth, and the Papiſts <hi>blot out the ſecond</hi> (which they do) and interpret the third only to prohibit <hi>falſe ſwearing</hi> (as ſome others have done) we have fairly quitted the firſt Table, and have nothing to get quit of but the ſecond, and we leave the whole world, as a generation of <hi>Belial,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any yoke at all.</p>
            <p n="6">6. After this it may not be amiſs for us to conſider, <hi>the Promiſes made to thoſe that keep the Lords Sabbaths, and the threatnings againſt the violaters of them.</hi> The firſt I ſhall inſtance in ſhall be that, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 17. from the 20. to the 24. <hi>v.</hi> their not obſerving the Sabbath according to the Command, is made their great crime: from the 24. <hi>v.</hi> is a Promiſe made to the better obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, <hi>v.</hi> 27. a threatning denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in caſe of neglect. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs, if you diligently hearken unto me, ſaith the Lord, to bring in no burthen through the gates of the City on the Sabbath day, but
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:109812:66"/> hallow the Sabbath to do no work therein: Then ſhall enter into the gates of this City Kings and Princes ſitting on the Throne of David, riding on Chariots and Horſes, they and their Princes, the men of</hi> Judah, <hi>and inhabitants of</hi> Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, <hi>and that City ſhall remain for ever.</hi> Here's a Promiſe of outward proſperity, and a ſtability in it. <hi>And they ſhall come from the Cities of</hi> Judah, <hi>and from the places about</hi> Hieruſalem, <hi>and from the land of</hi> Benjamin, <hi>and from the Plain, and from the Mountains, and from the South; bringing burnt-offerings and Sacrifices, and Meat-offerings, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, and bringing Sacrifices of praiſe unto the Lord our God:</hi> I will continue my Worſhip amongſt you in your own land, in its for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer purity, and glory. But what if this people will not ſanctifie the Lords Sabbaths? it follows, <hi>v.</hi> 27. <hi>But if you will not hearken unto me, to hallow the Sabbath day, and not to bear a burden, even entring in at the gates of</hi> Hieruſalem <hi>on the Sabbath day, then will I kindle a fire in the gates thereof, and it ſhall devour the Palaces of</hi> Hieruſalem, <hi>and it ſhall not be quenched:</hi> I will without remedy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy your City, and deprive you of all the proſperity wherewith I have bleſſed you. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.13. <hi>If thou turn away thy foot from
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:109812:66"/> the Sabbath, from doing thy pleaſure on my holy day, and call the Sabbath a delight, the holy of the Lord, honourable, and ſhalt honour him, not doing thine own wayes, nor finding thine own pleaſure, nor ſpeaking thy own words, then ſhalt thou delight thy ſelf in the Lord, and I will cauſe thee to ride upon the high places of the Earth, and feed thee with the heritage of Jacob thy father.</hi> Here is not only a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of temporall good, <hi>riding upon the high places of the Earth, inheriting the heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of Jacob,</hi> (which in generall you know was the bleſſing) but alſo of a ſpiritual mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>Thou ſhalt delight thy ſelf in the Lord:</hi> Now leſt any one ſhould think theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes are debts paid, fulfilled to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and concern not us, let us conſider yet ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Text, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.2, 3, 4, 5, &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that doth this, and the Son of man that layeth hold on it, that keepeth the Sabbath from polluting it, and keepeth his hand from doing evil. Neither let the Son of the ſtranger that hath joyned himſelf to the Lord, ſpeak, ſaying The Lord hath utterly ſeparated me from his people: Neither let the Eunuch ſay, Behold I am a dry tree. For thus ſaith the Lord, unto the Eunuchs that keep my Sabbaths, and chooſe the things that pleaſe me, and take hold of my
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:109812:67"/> Covenant, even unto them will I give in my houſe, and within my walls, a place, and a name better than that of Sons and Daughters: I will give them an everlaſting name that ſhall not be cut off,</hi> v. 5. <hi>Alſo the ſons of the ſtranger, that joyn themſelves to the Lord, to ſerve him, and to love the name of the Lord, to be his ſervants, every one that keepeth the Sabbath from pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it, and taketh hold on my Covenant,</hi> v. 6. <hi>Even them will I bring to my holy moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and make them joyfull in my Houſe of Prayer: their burnt-offerings, and their ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices ſhall be accepted upon mine Altar, for my Houſe ſhall be called an Houſe of Prayer for all people,</hi> v. 7. That this is a promiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the Goſpel-times, is plain enough from divers things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is made as a relief for <hi>Eunuchs</hi> and <hi>ſtrangers,</hi> who in regard of the <hi>partition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall</hi> ſet up by the Ceremonial Law, lay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der many diſcouragements, from joyning themſelves to the Lord.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It ſpeaks of a time to come when this Wall ſhould be pulled down. <hi>I will bring them,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It ſpeaks of a time when Gods Houſe was to be called an Houſe of Prayer for <hi>all People;</hi> which was not till Goſpel-times.
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:109812:67"/> The things promiſed are great and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. God promiſeth, 1. <hi>A place in his Houſe.</hi> 2. <hi>A Name better than that of Sons and Daughters, even an everlaſting Name that ſhall never be cut off.</hi> 3. <hi>To bring them to his holy mountain.</hi> 4. <hi>To accept their Sacrifices.</hi> 5. <hi>To make them joyfull in the houſe of Prayer.</hi> Promiſes, then which God could not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe more. Now who ſhall be made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of them. <hi>(Lord who ſhall dwell in thy Tabernacle, who ſhall abide in thy holy Hill?)</hi> Theſe things are promiſed, <hi>To the Eunuchs that keep the Lords Sabbaths. To the ſtrangers that keep the Sabbath from polluting it.</hi> All but thoſe of the Jewiſh Nation come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of Strangers all we that are Gentile Churches, are but Churches made up of Strangers, <hi>who have joyned our ſelves to the Lord,</hi> and <hi>taken hold of his Covenant.</hi> If we would be bleſſed with theſe things, if we will have a <hi>place in Gods houſe, an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting name that ſhall never be cut off,</hi> if we would be <hi>brought to Gods holy Mountain,</hi> if we would have God accept our ſervices, if we would be made joyfull in the houſe of Prayer, we muſt keep the Sabbath from polluting it.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:109812:68"/>7. <hi>Will example move us?</hi> to ſay nothing of the example of the ſervants of God in the Old Teſtament: The example of <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> as a Magiſtrate is there a famous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, recorded <hi>Nehem.</hi> 20.32. <hi>ch.</hi> 13, 15, 16, 17, 19. but let us look into the New Teſtament, and there firſt take our Lords example, who was a zealous obſerver of the Sabbath, the ſeventh day Sabbath, (for the other did not begin till his reſurrection.) <hi>Mar.</hi> 1.21. <hi>He on the Sabbath day went into the Synagogue, and taught,</hi> Mar. 6.2. <hi>When the Sabbath day was come, be began to teach in the Synagogues.</hi> Once for all, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.16. <hi>As his cuſtom was, he went into the Synagogue on the Sabbath day, and ſtood up for to read.</hi> It remains, that we ſhould be ſatisfied how he ſpent that time of the Sabbath, which he did not ſpend in acts of more ſolemn pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip: Something we find as to what he did, <hi>he healed the ſick,</hi> Joh. 5.10, 11, 12, 13, 14, <hi>&amp;c. Joh.</hi> 9.14. <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.7. &amp; 13. 12, 13, 14. <hi>Mar.</hi> 3.2, 3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we find him alſo on the Sabbath day at <hi>a feaſt, Luk.</hi> 14.1, 2, 3, &amp;c. and paſſing through the corn-fields, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Mar.</hi> 2.23. ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve but his diſcourſes upon his <hi>healing the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:109812:68"/> ſick,</hi> when he was at the Feaſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.1, 2, 3. when he paſſed through the Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fields, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Mar.</hi> 2.23. you will find them conſtantly ſpiritual, and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſuited to the Law of the Sabbath, <hi>not ſpeaking our own words.</hi> Concerning others we have no ſuch particular account, but in the general, <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.56. The wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men <hi>reſted</hi> on the Sabbath day, according to <hi>the commandment,</hi> they prepared <hi>ſpices</hi> and <hi>oyntments</hi> the night before, but they <hi>reſted the Sabbath day, according to Gods command:</hi> Through the whole hiſtory of the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> you read of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and other Chriſtians exact as to the keeping of the Sabbath; nor is it at all to our diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage that the <hi>women,</hi> Luk. 23. reſted on the <hi>Jewiſh Sabbath</hi> according to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, for at that time there was no other to reſt upon. We plead for no ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification of any other day than what God hath commanded, and fall under the fourth Commandment, which we have already proved that the Chriſtian Sabbath doth.</p>
            <p n="8">8. After all this may it not be worth your while to conſider, <hi>the difference of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:109812:69"/> that return which your awakened conſcience will make to you, when you have ſpent a Sabbath according to this rule; from that which your conſcience will make after a looſer obſervation.</hi> Do not your Conſciences ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times check you, when you have taken up too much of that ſacred time in ſleep, in dreſſing and trimming up your ſelves or houſes, in needleſs labours, in fooliſh pleaſures, in worldly diſcourſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly they may ſmite you in the actions, or preſently upon them; but if you caſt up your accounts at night, will they not chaſtiſe you b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fore you go to bed? will they not ſometimes tell you, you have that day done, or ſpake what you ought not to have ſaid, or done? The teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Conſcience is not wholly to be ſlighted in the caſe.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Laſtly, ſhall I referr you to thoſe who have taken notice of the <hi>Judgements of God</hi> upon <hi>Sabbath breakers:</hi> How many have <hi>periſhed</hi> in their <hi>pleaſures,</hi> in their <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours</hi> on that day? Dr. <hi>Beard,</hi> Mr. <hi>Clark,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bernard,</hi> have collected many of them. I am aware that too too many abuſe a Text of <hi>Solomon</hi> to avoid any force of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:109812:69"/> this argument, <hi>All things come alike to all men.</hi> Enough hath been ſpoken by other holy men, to ſhew that the Judgements of the Lord are not ſo to be ſlighted. 'Tis but very few years ſince, that many prodigious appearances in the <hi>Air, Water,</hi> &amp;c. and two or three <hi>Comets</hi> one after another were ſlighted, and laught at, but the dreadfull Judgements of the <hi>Plague,</hi> the <hi>Warr,</hi> the <hi>Fire of London,</hi> quickly baffled thoſe men of reaſon, and ſhewed us, that God doth not ordinarily go out of the courſe of Nature, but to ſhew ſome extraordinary work he is about, and to warn men to prepare to meet him. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>Lots</hi> Wife being turn'd into a Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of Salt, though our Saviour had not fixed a <hi>Remember</hi> to it, might have taught people, that it is a dangerous thing, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to a Divine Precept, to look back. We have a Precept to <hi>Remember to keep holy the Sabbath day;</hi> there are ſome that will not believe this obligeth us, but will adventure to <hi>work,</hi> to <hi>ſport,</hi> and take their uſual Recreations as on other dayes, God in theſe actions ſtrikes them <hi>lame, dead, &amp;c.</hi> Let who will ſlight theſe extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:109812:70"/> Diſpenſations of God, <hi>My ſoul ent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not thou into their ſecrets, unto their Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blies mine honour be not thou united.</hi> They ſhall all to me ſound — <hi>That Iſrael may hear and fear, and do no more ſo wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> It is time for me to finiſh this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe: Will now any of you ſay to me, What would you have us to do in this buſineſs, how would you have us ſanctifie the Sabbath unto the Lord? I anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I would have you the day or night before the Sabbath put all that buſineſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to your Familes in reference to the Sabbath, in as great a readineſs as you can. The women prepared their <hi>ſpices and oyntment</hi> over night which they were to uſe early <hi>in the morning</hi> after the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> Luk. 23.56. God allows us on the Sabbath to do things that are <hi>neceſſary;</hi> but we muſt take heed of creating <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities</hi> needleſly. We may make things neceſſary: It may be neceſſary I ſhould kindle a fire on the Sabbath, and ſo muſt have fuel, but not neceſſary I ſhould go that day to buy Coals, or cut down Wood, that might have been done the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:109812:70"/> day before. There's nothing truly neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary on that day, but what could not have been done before, nor cannot be put off longer.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>I would have you get up from your beds as ſoon that day as you uſe to do on other dayes,</hi> if not ſooner. It is a day of <hi>holy, ſpiritual reſt,</hi> not of <hi>ſenſuall, carnall reſt.</hi> It is a wretched profanation of that day, for people to make that day their ſleeping time above all other dayes, it ſpeaks a ſoul not well awakened with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of its duty on the Sabbath-day. Certainly, we had rather need be up ſooner from our beds that morning, that we may neither come late to Worſhip, nor make more haſte than good ſpeed, going out without any preparation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Family dutyes, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For <hi>ſuch buſineſſes as are acts of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to man or beaſt, or neceſſary for preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of either, I would have you do them without doubting.</hi> Our Saviour hath li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed both theſe: What is neceſſary for decency is as little to be doubted of; but take heed of ſpending too much time in trimmings and dreſſings, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:109812:71"/> exceſſive in proviſions of meat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Spend your time before you go to the Congregation which you can ſpare from ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary actions, (before mentioned) in private, Reading, Meditation, Prayer, or in inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Families, reading the Word to them, praying, ſinging Pſalms with them,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="5">5. After you have heard the Word preached, <hi>ſpend again your intermediate time in like manner, privately or with your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</hi> Diſcourſing alſo upon the Word which you have heard, or upon other ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſubjects as occaſion offers it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>After your hearing in the latter part of the day, do the ſame again:</hi> Read, hear, pray, catechize, ſing Pſalms, read good Books, diſcourſe upon ſpiritual ſubjects; what you have read or heard.</p>
            <p n="7">7. You need not doubt on this day, if occaſion be offered to <hi>viſit the ſick,</hi> or the <hi>Priſoners,</hi> to <hi>feed the hungry,</hi> to <hi>cloath the naked,</hi> with ſuch <hi>ſacrifice</hi> God is <hi>well-pleaſed,</hi> yea he <hi>loves this mercy</hi> better than <hi>other ſacrifice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. You muſt have your times on that day to <hi>eat</hi> and <hi>drink;</hi> by it your live<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are upheld, and your ſtrength, and you
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:109812:71"/> refreſhed, and made fit for your duties. But <hi>while you are eating and drinking, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member our Lords diſcourſes under the ſame circumſtances,</hi> Luk. 14.1, 2, 3. when he was at the <hi>Feaſt</hi> in the <hi>Phariſees</hi> houſe; He diſcourſeth of <hi>things lawfull on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> concerning <hi>humility, charity to the poor, concerning the Wedding Supper of the Goſpel,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This it is to ſanctifie a Sabbath unto the Lord, to keep a day as the Lord hath <hi>choſen.</hi> I beſeech you be not ſo vain as to think, that it is enough to <hi>reſt</hi> from <hi>ſin</hi> (which is your duty every day, and cannot be all the reſt of the Sabbath.) Nor that it is enough to <hi>reſt from labour,</hi> and you may ſpend the day in <hi>ſleep,</hi> or <hi>idleneſs,</hi> or <hi>ſports and paſtimes.</hi> None of all theſe (I am ſure) can be named <hi>an holy</hi> or <hi>ſpiritual reſt:</hi> Nor that it is enough to ſpend <hi>part of the day<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in <hi>religious du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties;</hi> God will not halve with you that day, he requires a <hi>whole day</hi> (at leaſt a whole artificial day, which the Sun mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureth to us) while we pretend to believe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Sabbath morall,</hi> let us live as if indeed we did believe it. Whiles we contend for the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:109812:72"/> 
               <hi>Chriſtian Sabbath,</hi> in evidence of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of Chriſts being come in the fleſh, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yling and <hi>reſurrection,</hi> againſt the <hi>Jew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> who deny Chriſt ſo come, and our <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thren;</hi> who though acknowledging Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> come, yet doubt whether as <hi>Lord of the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bath</hi> he made a change of the day. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> us not our ſelves run into a greater erro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of keeping no Sabbath at all.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
